<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of Episcopal confirmation in two discourses / by B. Camfield.</title>
            <author>Camfield, Benjamin, 1638-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14520</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11713596</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11713596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48306</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48306)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 526:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of Episcopal confirmation in two discourses / by B. Camfield.</title>
                  <author>Camfield, Benjamin, 1638-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 106, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Chiswel...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of orginal in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48306:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48306:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OF EPISCOPAL Confirmation: IN TWO DISCOURSES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> B. Camfield, <hi>Rector of Aileſton near Leiceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>D. Chryſoſt. Hom. <hi>9.</hi> in Epiſt. ad Hebr.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Chiſwel,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard. 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:48306:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48306:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Thomas,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> my much Honoured <hi>Dioceſan.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AFter I had received your Lordſhips Command for <hi>Preaching,</hi> which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came me neither to reſiſt nor diſpute; debating with my ſelf what <hi>Subject</hi> were moſt proper to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon in ſuch an Aſſembly; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined at laſt upon <hi>this of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which for many years hath been much in my thoughts, thoſe excellent words of the Learned and Reverend Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> having long ſince left in me a very deep impreſſion;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. Praef.</hi> § 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>That ſince the <hi>Faith it ſelf</hi> once delivered, and the <hi>two Sacraments</hi> of the New Covenant, inſtituted by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſtrictly commanded unto all; there is nothing which can
<pb facs="tcp:48306:3"/>
                  <hi>more ſtrongly oblige to a ſincere, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and durable obedience unto the Evangelical Law;</hi> nothing from the <hi>diligent and prudent adminiſtration whereof more plentiful Fruits</hi> may be hoped by the Chriſtian Church; and nothing, laſtly, whoſe <hi>neglect or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performance (pro forma &amp; ex opere, ut aiunt, operato)</hi> ſeemeth <hi>more perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and deſtructive unto piety.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>When therefore I had digeſted my Meditations and Collections upon this Argument into the <hi>enſuing method,</hi> (which is the <hi>onely thing almoſt peculiar</hi> to them) I could not eaſily be divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to any <hi>other</hi> Theme, had Time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a longer deliberation; though to ſome this might ſeem (as matters fell out) the <hi>leſs opportune by reaſon of your Lordſhips abſence,</hi> neceſſitated by thoſe Infirmities of Age and Bodily Indiſpoſitions, which then with a more than ordinary violence arreſted your perſon, to your <hi>own regret,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly
<pb facs="tcp:48306:3"/>upon this account, no leſs than <hi>our unhappineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among the Hearers <hi>notwithſtanding</hi> it met with a candid entertainment and general welcom; and ſo I hope it may do when it comes thus <hi>abroad</hi> into the world, <hi>(enlarged and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with another practical Diſcourſe to the ſame purpoſe)</hi> on no other deſign than to promote a common good.</p>
            <p>And I am the rather moved to Print it at <hi>this juncture of time,</hi> becauſe over and above the uſefulneſs of the <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſubject,</hi> it contains a <hi>moſt convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive evidence and demonſtration on the behalf of Dioceſan Epiſcopacy,</hi> (which ſome have <hi>ſpitefully</hi> renewed their old grudge and quarrels againſt) and the <hi>poſſibility of exerciſing Diſcipline in a Dioceſan Church,</hi> did not the <hi>too culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble neglects of many among us add too keen an edge to that exception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that it may ſhew it ſelf with the greater confidence of <hi>ſucceſs,</hi> as it
<pb facs="tcp:48306:4"/>was penn'd and uttered in obedience to your <hi>Lordſhips injunction,</hi> ſo the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it moſt humbly betakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to your <hi>Lordſhips Patronage,</hi> cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a benign and favourable recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from your <hi>Paternity,</hi> of this ſmall Preſent and Pledge of that great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance, which is ever due from,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips</hi> In all Filial Duty and Service, <hi>Benj. Camfield.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48306:4"/>
            <head>TO THE Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Argument here treated of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves ſufficiently for</hi> its own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance and uſefulneſs, <hi>as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared abundantly in the enſuing pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Nor may I arrogate any thing to my ſelf in the handling of it, after ſo many worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, unleſs perhaps the</hi> perſpicuity and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicalneſs of the digeſtion and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>and that in ſuch a manner, as both to</hi> recommend the thing from its moſt proper Topicks, <hi>and</hi> direct withall to the moſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful adminiſtration and obſervance <hi>of it. But that which more peculiarly inſtigated me to this publication, was the deep ſenſe I have, not onely of the too great</hi> neglect, <hi>and general</hi> need of Confirmation among the people, <hi>and the</hi> ſeaſonableneſs of perſuading them earneſtly, <hi>in theſe fickle and uncertain times,</hi> with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of heart to cleave unto their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>but the neceſſity alſo which</hi> Epiſcopacy it ſelf <hi>appears to be in of ſome further</hi> Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <hi>againſt the freſh and virulent Aſſaults of troubleſom and malevolous</hi> Diſſenters, <hi>who ſeek to lay the foundations of a ſtrange kind of</hi> diſagreeing Union <hi>among Engliſh Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants in caſheering that</hi> Prelacy, <hi>which hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb facs="tcp:48306:5"/>not onely</hi> here, <hi>but (untill within little more than one Century) throughout the</hi> whole Chriſtian Church, from the very firſt plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it. <hi>Of which there is not I think any</hi> ſingle proof or inſtance <hi>more clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, than what is</hi> hereafter <hi>ſuggeſted;</hi> 
               <q>The cuſtom of the Churches, as S. <hi>Hierom</hi> words it, for the Biſhop to go forth to thoſe, who were baptized a far off in leſſer Cities by Prieſts and Deacons, to lay hands upon them for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking of the Holy Ghoſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Epiſcopal Confirmation, <hi>as it hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the</hi> Apoſtolical Age, <hi>and practiſed</hi> ſucceſſively <hi>in the Chriſtian Church, is unto me a moſt undoubted evidence and confirmation of</hi> Dioceſan Epiſcopacy, <hi>and ſo I hope it may prove to all others, who will but have the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence impartially and coolly to examine and conſider of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if upon our manifold ſins and provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Divine</hi> Nemeſis <hi>ſhall ſo far overtake us, as to permit diſſatisfied and humourſom men</hi> once more <hi>to overturn our preſent Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we may firmly conclude upon</hi> former experience, <hi>that after divers Revolutions when their own Giddineſs hath tired them in the eager purſuit of</hi> Phanatic Innovations, <hi>there will be</hi> no fixation at laſt, <hi>but by</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again <hi>in a more ſober temper to what hath been ſo raſhly and impetuouſly deſtroyed by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48306:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>I will add nothing more now, but hearty prayers to God Almighty, that he would ſucceed</hi> theſe and all other great endeavours <hi>by his bleſſing, for the ſettling of us (if it be his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Will)</hi> upon ſuch peaceable principles, as may not ſever us from the Communion of Saints in that truly Catholic Church of Chriſt, which we retain in our Creed. <hi>And hereunto every underſtanding and orderly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian will readily ſubjoyn his moſt affectionate and zealous</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Ep. to Reader p. ult. l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> good endeavours. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 9. ſpeaks) <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 24. their <hi>r.</hi> thoſe. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 17. looſe. <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>marg.</hi> Circa A.D. 400. <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>dele</hi> by. <hi>l.</hi> 7. would have. <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 3. our own nation. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>l. ult.</hi> this. <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>marg.</hi> ipſae. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 43. <hi>l.</hi> 10, 11. managed. <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 46. <hi>l.</hi> 28. to be obſerved. <hi>p.</hi> 47. <hi>l.</hi> 22. audibly. <hi>p.</hi> 55. <hi>l. ult. &amp; p.</hi> 56. <hi>l.</hi> 1. we are confirmed. <hi>ib. marg.</hi> Melchiadis. <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 64. <hi>l.</hi> 17, 18, 19. <hi>dele</hi> c.c.c. <hi>p.</hi> 67. <hi>l.</hi> 24. Spalato. <hi>p</hi> 76. <hi>l.</hi> 29. principal. <hi>p.</hi> 85. <hi>l.</hi> 11, 12. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable. <hi>p.</hi> 87. <hi>l.</hi> 2. Secondly, the heart. <hi>p.</hi> 88. <hi>l. ult.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 89. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>l.</hi> 10. they were both. <hi>p.</hi> 91. <hi>l.</hi> 15. to be Chriſtians. <hi>p.</hi> 92. <hi>l.</hi> 17. plauſible. <hi>p.</hi> 94. <hi>l.</hi> 5. panes. <hi>p.</hi> 102. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contents p.</hi> 1. <hi>l. ult.</hi> obſignation. <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 24. as well. <hi>p. ult. l. penult.</hi> general motives, <hi>dele</hi> and exhortations.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48306:6"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48306:6"/>
                  <p>A Diſcourſe of CONFIRMATION: DELIVERED At the <hi>Primary Viſitation</hi> of the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>THOMAS,</hi> L. Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> Held at S. <hi>Martins Leiceſter, Sept.</hi> 22. 1679. And ſince enlarged.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With a ſhort Appendix thereunto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Inſolentiſſimae inſaniae eſt, exiſtimare non rectè fieri quod ab univerſa Eccleſia fit. <bibl>
                        <hi>D. Aug. ep. 118.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48306:7"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48306:7"/>
                  <head>OF Epiſcopal Confirmation.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Heb. 6.2.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Of the Doctrine of Baptiſms, and of Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of Hands.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THE Apoſtle, in the <hi>foregoing verſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> mentions the <hi>Principles of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt.</hi> The Margin hath it from the Greek, the <hi>Word of the beginning of Chriſt;</hi> or by an eaſie <hi>tranſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which our Tranſlation follows, the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Doctrine of Chriſt;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>Camerarius</hi> gloſſeth it; <hi>Sermonem qui in Chriſto rudes inchoat,</hi> as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> render it, <hi>the inſtruction which initiates novices or beginners in Chriſt.</hi> The ſame which in the <hi>precedent chapter</hi> he calls the <hi>firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Oracles of God;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ch. 5.12. Ch. 6.1.</note> and here again by a <hi>known Figure,</hi> the <hi>foundation,</hi> that is, <hi>the rudiments of Chriſtianity,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Haec omnia pertinere ad</hi> ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Neophytorum <hi>ſatis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertéque Scriptura teſtatur.</hi> D. Aug. de fide &amp; operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, c. 11.</note> or the <hi>Chriſtians A, B, C;</hi> the chief elements whereof he thus <hi>enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merates;</hi> 
                     <q>Of repentance from dead works, and of faith to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, the Doctrine of Baptiſms and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48306:8"/>of Laying on of Hands, and of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, and of Eternal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will not now trouble you with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Opinions among Expoſitors about the <hi>diſtinct way of reckoning</hi> of them up. If we take them as they lie <hi>moſt obvious</hi> to our view,
<note place="margin">B. <hi>Taylors</hi> Diſcourſe of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. p. 45.</note> then (as a <hi>right reverend and learned Author</hi> ſpeak, (<q>Here are <hi>ſix fundamental points of S. Pauls Catechiſm,</hi> which he laid as the foundation or the beginning of the Inſtitution of the Chriſtian Church; and amongſt theſe <hi>Impoſition of Hands,</hi> (which the Apoſtles uſed in <hi>confirming the Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">And that <hi>here</hi> it muſt be <hi>ſo under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,</hi> he <hi>proves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly,</hi> p. 46, 47, 48.</note>, <hi>and invocating the Holy Ghoſt upon them</hi>) is reckoned as a <hi>part of the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And therefore they who deny it, ſaith <hi>he,</hi> dig up <hi>foundations.</hi> And when S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it the <hi>Doctrine of the Laying on of Hands,</hi> it does not onely appear to be a <hi>laſting Miniſtry</hi> becauſe no part of the Chriſtian Doctrine can be changed or abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, but hence alſo it appears to be of <hi>Divine Inſtitution.</hi> For if it were not, S. <hi>Paul</hi> had been guilty of that which our Bleſſed Saviour reproves in the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and ſhould have <hi>taught for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines the commands of men;</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it cannot be ſuppoſed, it muſt needs follow, that this Doctrine of Impoſition of Hands, or Confirmation, is <hi>Apoſtolical and Divine.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48306:8"/>
                  <p> But upon a <hi>ſtricter examination</hi> of the words, the <hi>chief ſtreſs</hi> of all ſeems unto me, I confeſs, to be laid upon the <hi>two formoſt heads,</hi> (wherein S. <hi>Paul</hi> elſewhere ſumms up the <hi>whole counſel of God</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 20.21. and that agrees well enough with his <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 2 Tim. 1.13.</note>) namely, <q>
                        <hi>Repentance from dead works and faith towards God:</hi>
                     </q> which certainly includes <hi>fidelity and obedience to his commands,</hi> as well as <hi>belief of the Creed,</hi> whereof the <hi>two concluding branches</hi> are thoſe laſt ſpecified, <q>
                        <hi>the reſurrection of the dead, and eternal judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi>
                     </q> (which the <hi>ſame Apoſtle</hi> in like manner <hi>particularly</hi> refers to, when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his <hi>hope Godwards</hi> before the <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Caeſarea, Acts</hi> 24.15.) And then the words of the <hi>Text</hi> (there being <hi>no particles of connexion</hi> between them) may fitly enough be read by way of <hi>appoſition</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,
<note place="margin">Vide Calv. in loc.</note> as <hi>in a Parentheſis (the Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms and of Laying on of Hands)</hi> not ſo much to intend the recital of <hi>two other different heads of Chriſtian Doctrine,</hi> as the <hi>time when account was given and taken of this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, viz.</hi> at <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which in their firſt Ages was commonly diſpenſed to the <hi>Adult,</hi> and at <hi>Confirmation after Baptiſm</hi> by the Impoſition or Laying on of Hands: <hi>q.d.</hi> 
                     <q>The foundation of Repentance from dead works, and Faith towards God, being the Chriſtian Doctrine, <hi>an account whereof was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48306:9"/>given and taken at Baptiſm and the Laying on of Hands.</hi> The Doctrine delivered and profeſſed at Baptiſm and the Laying on of Hands,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>W. Par. &amp; Annot. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>ford, in loc.</hi> 1675.</note> as a <hi>late worthy Paraphraſt</hi> hath it.</q> Or (as he ſpeaks <hi>more at large</hi>) <q>The prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, whereof publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion was made at Baptiſm by Converts, and at the times of Impoſition of Hands by thoſe that had received Baptiſm in their Infancy.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, we have here <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> the door or entrance of Chriſtianity, called <hi>Baptiſms,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the <hi>plural</hi> number, perhaps becauſe <hi>many were baptized at once:</hi> or <hi>put for the ſingular,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib. de ſide &amp; operibus c.</hi> 11.</note> as chap. 9.23. (ſo S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reads it, <hi>Lavacri Doctrinae:</hi>) or elſe with reference to the <hi>threefold merſion then made uſe of,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>one Baptiſm,</hi> though in this one were anciently uſed <hi>many merſions or waſhings</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The Reference of <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naes</hi> and <hi>others</hi> to a <hi>Triplex Baptiſmus, Fluminis, Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, Sanguinis,</hi> ſeems too much ſtrained. And ſo alſo the <hi>Duplex Baptiſmus, Joannis &amp; Chriſti,</hi> which ſome here diſcourſe of.</note>. And then <hi>Impoſition of hands for Confirmation,</hi> but <hi>previous thereunto</hi> Inſtruction in the <hi>firſt elements</hi> or principles of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, by a <hi>plain and practical Catechiſm, ſuch as that which is appointed by our Church to be learned by every one, before they be brought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For whatever low and contemptible thoughts ſome may have of our <hi>Church Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm,</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48306:9"/>it is certainly <hi>moſt agreeable to the Apoſtolical patern here ſet before us;</hi> viz. the foundation of <hi>Repentance from dead works and Faith towards God;</hi> that is, <hi>the ſumm of our Engagements as we are Chriſtians,</hi> or <hi>the vow of our Chriſtianity,</hi> to forſake the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh; to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, (among which are the Reſurrection of the dead, and Eternal Judgment) and to keep God's holy Will and Commandments, and walk in the ſame all the days of our Life; ſhewing thus all good <hi>fidelity</hi> towards that God in whom we believe. This is nothing elſe you ſee but <hi>a Paraphraſe upon Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from dead works, and Faith towards God:</hi> and ſo it appears to have been <hi>deſign'd by the Church.</hi> You may obſerve it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly in <hi>the Queſtions and Anſwers touching Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q.</hi> What is required of perſons to be Baptized?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A. Repentance,</hi> whereby they forſake ſin; and <hi>Faith,</hi> whereby they ſtedfaſtly believe the Promiſes made to them in that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q.</hi> Why then are Infants Baptized, when by reaſon of their tender age they cannot perform them?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they promiſe them <hi>both</hi> by their Sureties; which Promiſe when they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48306:10"/>come to age themſelves are bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>In which words it is moſt evident, that <hi>Repentance</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> are declared to be the <hi>importance of the vow and promiſe made at Baptiſm.</hi> And ſo the Church Catechiſm, which in the main branches of it is nothing elſe but <hi>a plain Comment upon the Contents of this vow and promiſe,</hi> correſponds exactly with <hi>that in the Apoſtles Age</hi> the Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt <hi>then propounded to beginners;</hi> or the <hi>milk for babes,</hi> as our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle alſo calls it, <hi>chap.</hi> 5.12, 13. that <hi>ſincere milk of the word, which they ſhould hunger and thirſt after,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>to grow thereby;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>But I will ſay no more of this, deſigning onely the choice of the Text to <hi>ground a Diſcourſe about Confirmation upon,</hi> for the better preparation of thoſe who ſhould have been confirmed by our <hi>Right Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dioceſan</hi> in this his Viſitation, had it pleaſed Almighty God to have permitted him health and ſtrength to have come <hi>in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> among us, according to his good and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intentions.</p>
                  <p>And now I had thought to have diverted wholly from <hi>this ſubject</hi> (as leſs pertinent and agreeable) unto ſomething elſe; but that I really fear, the <hi>long diſuſe of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred performance among us, may occaſion in ſome too great ignorance or indifference about
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48306:10"/>it, if not averſation from and diſguſt againſt it.</hi> And therefore I will hope your favour, while I proceed upon the <hi>ſame</hi> Argument, that though we are ſo unhappy at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as to be deprived of the <hi>bleſſing,</hi> we may yet keep alive among us the <hi>Chriſtian deſires</hi> of embracing all opportunities for the obtaining of it.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall forbear to make any further Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, but for method ſake digeſt what I have to offer unto your thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this matter under <hi>theſe five</hi> heads:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the general, of the <hi>Names whereby it is known.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of the <hi>Scripture paterns and grounds for it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Of the <hi>Ceremony uſed in it,</hi> the <hi>Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Biſhops hands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Of the <hi>Qualification of the perſons ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing to it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And 5. Of the <hi>important uſefulneſs of the whole Rite and Action.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of each of which now by Gods help with your patience briefly in order.</p>
                  <p>And firſt in the general, of the <hi>Names whereby it is known and called.</hi> And here, 1. we ſhould take notice of that before us in the <hi>Text,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>impoſition or laying on of hands;</hi> ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the Rite evermore attending the Miniſtration of it, the <hi>Apoſtles firſt, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48306:11"/>them Biſhops laying on their hands on the parties confirmed by them.</hi> Of which I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to diſcourſe more particularly <hi>after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by it ſelf,</hi> and therefore wave the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proſecution of it in this place.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, it is alſo called among the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Perfection;</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Dionyſ. Areap. Poſt fontem ſupereſt ut</hi> perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio <hi>fiat, quando ad invocationem Sacerdotis Spiritus Sanctus infunditur.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De Sacr. l. 3. c. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>D. Ambroſ.</hi>) the perſon confirmed being look'd upon as a <hi>perfect</hi> or <hi>complete Chriſtian,</hi> when he hath thus <hi>actually</hi> taken the Engagements made in his name at Baptiſm, upon himſelf, and received the <hi>ſtrengthening ſupplies</hi> of the Spirit,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Albaſpin.</hi> not. in can. 77. Concil. <hi>Elibert.</hi>
                     </note> as well as his <hi>new birth.</hi> And none was reputed a <hi>perfect Chriſtian,</hi> or <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with as ſuch,</hi> till his Confirmation— So the <hi>Author of the Imperfect Work on Saint Matthew,</hi> under the name of S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> tells us, (ſpeaking of <hi>not giving holy things unto dogs</hi>) <q>That the holy grace of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt is to be given to them onely,
<note place="margin">Hom. 17.</note> 
                        <hi>(qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>amper Baptiſmum facti ſunt filii Dei, &amp; per manuum impoſitionem)</hi> who are already <hi>made the Sons of God by Baptiſm, and by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands;</hi> that is, <hi>baptized and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed:</hi> it is <hi>Childrens bread.</hi>
                     </q> And ſo we have it in <hi>our own Rubric;</hi> that <q>None ſhall be admitted to the holy Communion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48306:11"/>he be confirmed, or be ready and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be confirmed.</q> Both agreeable to the 48 <hi>Canon of the Council of Laodicea;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A.D.</hi> 364.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; <q>Perſons after Baptiſm muſt be anointed with the Heavenly Chriſm or Unction, that they may be partakers of the Kingdom of God—For ſo I am to tell you,</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that it is alſo familiarly named among the Ancients <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Chriſm or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>Dionyſius;</hi> h. e.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Eccleſiae Hierarch. Catech.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Perfectivum ſeu conſecratorium chriſma;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in S. <hi>Cyril; Divini Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis unctio, &amp; Chriſma Eccleſiaſticum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>De gub. Dei, l.</hi> 3.</note> in <hi>Salvian.</hi>) And this name poſſibly might ariſe from the <hi>gift of the Holy Ghoſt here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred,</hi> (that is, an <hi>additional meaſure of his graces,</hi> as we ſhall ſee afterwards) whoſe operations are in the ſacred Scriptures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled unto <hi>oyl,</hi> the <hi>oyl of gladneſs;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.8. Heb. 1.9. 2 Cor. 1.22 1 Jo. 2.27</note> from whence in the New Teſtament Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are ſaid alſo to receive an <hi>unction, or anointing.</hi> From which phraſe of <hi>unction</hi> and <hi>alluſion thereunto,</hi> it came to paſs very early in the Church, that the Ceremony of <hi>Anealing or Anointing with oyl was practiſed both in Baptiſm and Confirmation.</hi> And as our bleſſed Lord and Saviour is called <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from his being plentifully <hi>anointed with the Holy Ghoſt, moſt viſibly in his deſcent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48306:12"/>upon him after his Baptiſm;</hi> ſo may we with propriety (as ſome conceive) be named <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> from our being <hi>anointed with the ſame Spirit;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A. D.</hi> 170.</note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oph. Antioch. l.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Autolych.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>But however this appellation of <hi>Chriſm</hi> is frequent (as I ſaid) among the Ancients; yet it ſeems <hi>not peculiar unto Confirmation,</hi> Anointing having been uſed alſo at <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> as I intimated; &amp; <hi>both Baptiſm and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation are perfect and entire enough without it,</hi> ſince we never read that the Apoſtles uſed it in <hi>either</hi> of them. And therefore that Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ham. de Confirm. c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2.</note> as it was <hi>freely at firſt taken up</hi> in the Church, ſo upon the ſame Chriſtian Liberty doubtleſs is <hi>as freely to be omitted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, it hath alſo been called <hi>Conſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio, conſigning or ſealing; (Signaculum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 73.</note> by S. <hi>Cyprian;</hi>) the <hi>Lords ſign, or ſignature, or ſeal; (Signaculum ſpiritale,</hi> by S.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Sacram. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) a <hi>ſpiritual ſign, ſignature, or ſeal.</hi> And thus probably it was named from the <hi>custom of ſigning the confirmed party with the ſign of the Croſs at his anointing— Inſcripta oleo fronti ſignacula,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caſſand. Schol. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ymn. Prud.</note> as <hi>Prudentius</hi> the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Poet, who lived <hi>about S. Jeroms time,</hi> hath it. Unleſs we ſhould rather chuſe to refer it to a <hi>more ſpiritual ſealing with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt,</hi> 
                     <q>the ſeal and aſſurance of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians inheritance, by whom we are ſealed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48306:12"/>to the day of Redemption, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13.
<note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol. Graec.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.30.</q> And the Apoſtle writes <hi>thus</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> (as an excellent perſon obſerves) <hi>who well underſtood his meaning, by remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering what was done to themſelves by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles but awhile before, Acts</hi> 19.6.
<note place="margin">B. <hi>Taylor</hi> of Confirm. p. 55.</note> who after they were baptized did lay their hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. And <hi>ſo they were ſealed,</hi> and <hi>ſo they received the Holy Spirit of promiſe;</hi> of which more by and by.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, that which is now become <hi>moſt familiar among us,</hi> and properly enough de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominative of the thing intended by it, is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>confirmation;</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it being to <hi>confirm, corroborate,</hi> and <hi>add ſtrength to our firſt Chriſtian Profeſſion;</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Conſtit. Apoſtol.</hi>) And by Gods bleſſing in anſwer to the prayers made on our behalf <hi>unto our Chriſtian gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ability of living anſwerably to that good profeſſion; (Tunc omne baptiſma legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Chriſtianitatis nomine confirmatur,</hi> as 'tis in an <hi>old Ordo Romanus.</hi>)
<note place="margin">In Oſſic. Sab. Paſch.</note> So that it is a Confirmation on <hi>both parts,</hi> both on <hi>Gods and ours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>We confirm and re-eſtabliſh our Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Covenant in our own names,</hi> ſeeking grace and ſtrength afreſh from God to fulfill and accompliſh it. And,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>God confirms the bleſſing of his Covenant unto us, by the kind reception of his peculiar
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48306:13"/>Miniſter,</hi> bleſſing of us from him and in his name, and thereby aſſuring us of his grace both to aſſiſt and reward us.</p>
                  <p>And upon the ſame account, Sixthly, it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Obſignation;</hi> being thus, a <hi>novation or renewing of the Covenant, Stipulation, and Promiſe on both parts made, as it were under Hand and Seal.</hi> In that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſtory which <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports from <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. D.</hi> 200.</note> of the young man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a certain <hi>Aſian Biſhop</hi> by S. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, whom after inſtruction he both <hi>baptized and confirmed;</hi> his Confirmation is expreſſed under the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt. l.</hi> 3.23.</note> 
                     <hi>the Seal of the Lord;</hi> as <hi>elſewhere in him,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>L.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 43.</note> to be <hi>ſealed by the Biſhop</hi> is to be <hi>confirmed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hereunto therefore the Reverend and Learned Dr.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Confirm. praef.</hi> § 8, 9</note> 
                     <hi>Hammond</hi> not unfitly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modates <hi>that Text of S. Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <q>The foundation of the Lord ſtandeth ſure,
<note place="margin">Id. Annot. in loc.</note> having this Seal, the Lord knoweth them that are his. And let every one that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the name of Chriſt depart from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</q> Where the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>Foundation,</hi> may import (ſaith he) as well <hi>a Covenant, a Bill of Contract, a Bond or Obligation, a Pledge or Pawn,</hi> (from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>pono) ſomewhat delivered as a ſecurity to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and ſo refers to the <hi>Covenant of God through Chriſt,</hi> which is here ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:48306:13"/>
                     <hi>firm and ſtable,</hi> and that firmitude demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by its <hi>Seal annexed,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, (which ſeems alſo to relate plainly to a <hi>Bill or a Bond;</hi>) and becauſe ſuch Seals had their <hi>Inſcription on both ſides,</hi> agreeable to the condition of the perſons contracting, accordingly there is here added a <hi>double print and inſcription upon the Seal, (Signaculi gemina facies, duplex epigraphe.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Ex parte Dei,</hi> on <hi>God's part,</hi> the <hi>image of the Divine Promiſe and Covenant,</hi> that he will be <hi>faithful and conſtant in the owning of his Servants.</hi> 
                     <q>The Lord knoweth them that are his.</q> Whereas he will ſay unto <hi>others,</hi> 'I never knew you. And,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Ex parte hominis,</hi> on <hi>Man's part,</hi> the <hi>expreſs image of his duty.</hi> 
                     <q>Let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt depart from iniquity:</q> that is, every one that writes himſelf Chriſtian, and expects Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Goſpel Covenant; every one that gives up his name to Chriſt, and hopes for reward from him, muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that he is bound by a ſevere and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſible Law, to renounce all diſhoneſty, impurity, impiety, and to lead a godly, righteous, and ſober life, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. to cleanſe himſelf from all filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>both theſe together make the ſealing of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48306:14"/>the Goſpel Covenant complete;</hi> and <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the firſt time of our perſonal and public claim to this Covenant, and the ratification of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But thus much of the <hi>Names</hi> whereby it is known,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ham. L'Eſtrange,</hi> Alliance of Divine Offices, p. 248. Dr. <hi>Ham. de Confirm. p.</hi> 80.</note> 
                     <hi>moſt of which</hi> are thought by ſome to have been derived from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21, 22. <q>Now he which eſtabliſheth (or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth</hi>) us with you in Chriſt, and hath <hi>anointed</hi> us is God; who hath alſo <hi>ſealed</hi> us, and given the <hi>earneſt</hi> of his Spirit in our hearts;</q> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.— It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the <hi>imparting of ſome ſpiritual</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>or Gift, to the end we may be eſtabliſhed or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</hi> In order to which S. <hi>Paul</hi> longed ſo much for a proſperous journey to viſit the <hi>Romans, chap.</hi> 1.11, 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>I proceed now, Secondly, to ſpeak more particularly of the <hi>Scripture paterns and grounds for the thing it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are among the <hi>Fathers</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this Rite of Confirmation ſufficiently <hi>figured out and pointed to in the eminent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of the Holy Ghoſt upon our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our after his Baptiſm, in the form of a Dove overſpreading him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ham. de Confirm. p.</hi> 143. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Cyril. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>atech.</hi> 3. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d. p.</hi> 171.</note> 
                     <hi>S. Matth.</hi> 3.— And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the <hi>deſcent of the ſame Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit upon the Apoſtles at Pentecoſt, ſitting upon each of them, Acts</hi> 2. Of which <hi>Euſebius Emiſſenus</hi> (or as ſome think, <hi>Eucherius Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunenſis,</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48306:14"/>who died about the Year of our Lord 454) thus ſpeaks in his <hi>Homily upon Pentecoſt;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vide Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. Dialog. adverſus Luciferian.</note> 
                     <q>What now the Impoſition of hands in the confirming young Chriſtians doth give to every one, that then did the deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Believers beſtow upon all.</q> But I ſhall not inſiſt on <hi>either of theſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> having enlarged firſt on the <hi>example of Chriſt at Jordan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. § 1.</note> pleads very ſtrongly for the grounding of it upon <hi>that noted Text of our Saviours to Nichodemus, S. John</hi> 3.5. <q>Unleſs a man be born of water and of the Holy Ghoſt, he ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of God.</q> 
                     <hi>The moſt eaſie, intelligible, and clear ſenſe of which words he makes to be this;</hi> 
                     <q>Unleſs a man be <hi>baptized into Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>confirmed by the Spirit of Chriſt,</hi> he cannot enter into his Kingdom; that is, he is not perfectly adopted into the Chriſtian Religion, or fitted for the Chriſtian warfare.</q> And this he contends to be <hi>conſonant to the whole deſign of our bleſſed Saviour, and the analogie of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And <hi>to the ſame ſenſe S. Cyprian moſt evidently gloſſeth upon the place;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ep.</hi> 72. <hi>quae eſt ad Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phunum.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>(Tunc enim plenè ſanctificari, &amp; eſſe Dei filii poſſunt, ſi Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramento utroque naſcantur, cùm ſcriptum ſit, Niſi quis natus fuerit ex aqua &amp; ſpiritu, non poteſt intrare in regnum Dei.</hi>) But I ſhall wave the urging of <hi>this alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48306:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48306:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48306:16"/>
                  <p>We have an undoubted and remarkable inſtance of <hi>Apoſtolical practice</hi> for it, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. where <hi>Philip the Deacon</hi> having preached the Goſpel at <hi>Samaria,</hi> and thereby won many Converts, and <hi>baptized</hi> them, the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles at Jeruſalem</hi> hearing of it, ſend forth <hi>two of their own number, Peter and John;</hi> Who <q>(ſaith the <hi>ſacred Text,</hi> ver. 15. &amp;c.) when they were come down prayed for them, that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt:</q> and then <q>laid their hands on them, and they received the Holy Ghoſt.</q> It pleaſed God that thoſe admirable Gifts, called there the Holy Ghoſt, ſhould not ordinarily be conferred on the Baptized, but by the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hands,</hi> thereby to <hi>ſtrengthen the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of thoſe his Witneſſes,</hi> and by the ſame means <hi>promote the unity of the Church,</hi> through the reverend eſteem of thoſe chief Miniſters, as <hi>Grotius</hi> well notes.
<note place="margin">In locum.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In <hi>this ſtory</hi> now we have,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>perſons confirmed,</hi> the <hi>baptized Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi> who had believed and been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed aforehand in <hi>Philip's doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Miniſters of Confirmation, Peter and John,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſent from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on that very purpoſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What <hi>they did</hi> in Confirmation. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard of their <hi>faith</hi> in receiving the Word of God, and their <hi>baptiſm</hi> in profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that faith, they <hi>prayed for them</hi> that they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48306:16"/>might receive the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>and laid their hands upon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The <hi>conſequent effect thereof,</hi> they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> that is, the <hi>more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful effuſions of the Holy Ghoſt in his gifts and graces,</hi> which in that beginning of the Chriſtian Church were miraculous and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary; whereas the <hi>promiſe of the ſame Spirit holds good ſtill in ſome due proportion, unto the Chriſtians of all Ages to the worlds end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Thoſe (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ep.</hi> 73. <hi>quae eſt ad Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baianum.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Cyprian</hi>) who believed in <hi>Samaria,</hi> had believed with a <hi>true faith,</hi> and were baptized in the Church, which is but one, and to which alone it is permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to give the grace of Baptiſm, and to loſe ſins. And therefore having obtein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>legitimate and Eccleſiaſtical Baptiſm,</hi> ought not again to be baptized; but <hi>that onely which was yet wanting</hi> to be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them by <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> that by <hi>prayer and impoſition of hands</hi> the Holy Ghoſt might be invoked and poured forth upon them:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Circa A.D.</hi> 250.</note> 
                        <hi>which now alſo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom obſerved among us,</hi> that they who are baptized in the Church, be offered to the Governors of the Church, and by our prayer and impoſition of hands obtain the Holy Ghoſt, and be conſummated (or perfected) with the Lord's Seal or Signa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture—</q> Where we ſee he applies the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48306:17"/>patern</hi> to the <hi>cuſtom retained ſtill by the Church in Confirmation,</hi> the practice whereof in <hi>his days</hi> he doth well deſcribe, and intimates alſo the <hi>requiſiteneſs of it after Baptiſm,</hi> though never ſo <hi>legitimate,</hi> when he calls it <hi>Id quod deerat,</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>That which was yet wanting.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>anoher inſtance</hi> we have <hi>Acts</hi> 19. where we find S. <hi>Paul confirming thoſe who were taught and baptized before at Epheſus,</hi> ver. 6. <q>When <hi>Paul</hi> laid his hands upon them (ſaith the <hi>Text</hi>) the Holy Ghoſt came upon them, and they ſpoke with Tongues and propheſied.</q> (They were baptized, ſaith <hi>Grotius</hi> on the place by ſome other Chriſtian; but God, to commend the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical office</hi> would not communicate thoſe gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, untill the hand of <hi>ſome Apoſtle</hi> had touched them. And though he be not bound to this or any other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance, yet ſuch was the method of his <hi>ordinary diſpenſation</hi> then among them.) Here now we have 12 <hi>perſons firſt taught, and then baptized in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, and then afterwards by the impoſition of the Apoſtles hands receiving the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted according to the <hi>ſpecial way and exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of thoſe firſt times,</hi> in his viſible and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gifts. And to <hi>this S. Paul him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſeems to refer, touching theſe Epheſians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by him,</hi> (as upon occaſion I before in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48306:17"/>part ſuggeſted) <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. <q>In whom alſo after that ye believed, ye were ſealed with the Holy Spirit of Promiſe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor ought any to be offended or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced, becauſe we find not the <hi>like gifts of the Spirit</hi> continued now in the Church: <q>The Holy Ghoſt (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> 
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) is not now given by Impoſition of hands with <hi>temporal and ſenſible miracles,</hi> as it was at the firſt for the commendation of the Faith, and the enlargment of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Church; who now expects it? &amp;c. But we are now to underſtand that <hi>after an inviſible and hidden manner Divine Charity is inſpired into their hearts by the bond of peace</hi>
                     </q>—And thus as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath it to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt. ch.</hi> 12. <q>There are <hi>diverſities of gifts,</hi> but the <hi>ſame Spirit</hi>
                     </q>—Not the <hi>ſame gifts</hi> now as then, yet the <hi>ſame ſpirit</hi> ſtill.</p>
                  <p>To <hi>theſe inſtances</hi> of Apoſtolical practice therefore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and S. <hi>Jerom,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Circa A.D.</hi> 203.</note> do both freely appeal for the <hi>juſtifying of this ſacred cuſtom,</hi> (as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> you heard before did) and that without any colour for the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Montaniſm</hi> in the caſe, as ſome have fondly pleaſed themſelves to imagine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The Diſciples prayed (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Trinit. l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> 
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) that the Holy Ghoſt might come upon thoſe, on whom they laid their hands. <hi>Which ſame cuſtom</hi> the Church doth alſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48306:18"/>now obſerve in her Governors or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then for S.
<note place="margin">Dialog. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferian.</note> 
                     <hi>Jerom:</hi> 
                     <q>Doſt thou not know (ſaith he) that this is the <hi>cuſtom of the Churches,</hi> to lay hands afterwards on the baptized, and ſo to invocate the Holy Ghoſt? Doſt thou demand of me, <hi>Where is it written?</hi> I anſwer, In the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles:</hi> and, were there no Scripture Authority at all to ſupport it, the <hi>conſent of the whole world</hi> might in this ſupply the room of a Precept; for there are alſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things obſerved by <hi>Tradition</hi> in the Churches, which have taken to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Authority of a written Law; as the <hi>threefold immerſion</hi> in Baptiſm, &amp;c.</q>— This 'tis true he ſpeaks in the <hi>perſon of Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferianus;</hi> but then he brings in <hi>Orthodoxus</hi> making a Reply <hi>by way of Acknowledgment to the ſame;</hi> 
                     <q>I do not indeed deny this <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> to be the <hi>cuſtom of the CHurches,</hi> that the Biſhop go forth to thoſe who were baptized afar off in leſſer Cities by Prieſts and Deacons, to lay hands upon them for the invocating of the Holy Ghoſt—</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Deſervedly therefore doth <hi>our Church</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer us to the <hi>ſame Apoſtolical warrant.</hi> 
                     <q>Upon whom, after the <hi>the example of the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> we have now laid our hands.</q> So in the <hi>Prayer at Confirmation.</hi> — <q>(the Fathers of the Primitive Church taking occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48306:18"/>and <hi>founding themſelves upon the ſaid acts and deeds of the Apoſtles.</hi>)</q> So in the <hi>neceſſary Doctrine and Erudition for any Chriſtian man, p.</hi> 42.—<q>For as much as it hath been a ſolemn ancient, and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cuſtom in the Church of God <hi>continued from the Apoſtles time</hi>—</q> So in King <hi>James's Canons, Can.</hi> 60.</p>
                  <p>I have purpoſely omitted to inſtance fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in S. <hi>Paul and Barnabas,</hi> and <hi>others, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting ſeveral Churches,</hi> and <q>
                        <hi>confirming the Souls of the Diſciples in them,</hi> exhorting them to continue in the Faith, and with purpoſe of heart to cleave unto the Lord, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 14.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.32.</q> Becauſe we have not the like <hi>expreſs mention</hi> there of any <hi>impoſition of hands,</hi> though it may be we might with probability enough <hi>ſuppoſe it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Inſtances now of Apoſtolical Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice do give light unto,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> and receive further light from, what we have before us in the <hi>Text; where, after the mention of the doctrine of Baptiſms, we find Laying on of hands; (Nempe Epiſcoporum in confirmatione Neophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Anſelm) viz.</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>of Biſhops in the confirmation of new Diſciples</hi>—Impoſition of hands (ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtom) whereby they received the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </q> And <hi>Theophylact,</hi> in like manner, <hi>referring particularly to the ſtory of S. Paul's laying on his hands upon them at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48306:19"/>Epheſus, Acts</hi> 19.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Hom. 9. in Ep. ad Hebr.</note>—<q>By Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands (ſaith S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi>) it is believed that the Spirit may be received; <hi>which is wont to be done after Baptiſm by the Biſhop,</hi> for the Confirmation of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Church.</q>—Whereunto may be an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ed the 38th.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ranze</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ma <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>bert. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oncil.</note> 
                     <hi>and</hi> 77th. <hi>Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of the Council of Eliberis or Elvira,</hi> about the time of Pope <hi>Sylveſter the firſt</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 316.</note>, which require <hi>the Biſhop ſhould perſect or confirm by his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, thoſe who had not been baptized in his preſence.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>irca A.D.</hi> 200.</note>—And <hi>Tertullian long before</hi> having ſpoken of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> adds, <hi>(Dehinc ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus imponitur per benedictionem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo c.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8</note> 
                     <hi>advocans &amp; invitans Spiritum Sanctum</hi>) <q>Then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the hand is laid on by way of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Id de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrect. Carn. c.</hi> 8.</note> calling to and inviting down the Holy Spirit.</q> And again ſaith he in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place: <q>The Fleſh is <hi>waſhed,</hi> that the Soul may be without ſpot: the Fleſh is <hi>anointed,</hi> that the Soul may be conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: the Fleſh <hi>is ſigned,</hi> that the Soul alſo may be defended: the Fleſh is <hi>overſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Impoſition of hands,</hi> that the Soul alſo may be illuminated by the Spirit, &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the <hi>ſame way the generality of modern Interpreters (whatever have been their practice) ſtill inclines.</hi> I will inſtance in ſome of <hi>greateſt name and eminence</hi> among the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and Proteſtant Churches,</hi> the rather
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48306:19"/>becauſe this <hi>Rite of Confirmation</hi> hath been unhappily decried and declamed againſt as a <hi>Relique of Popiſh Superſtition</hi> to be aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned and rejected by us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The Apoſtle (ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> on the place) calls the <hi>ſolemn Rites or ſtated days of Baptizing</hi> by the name of <hi>Baptiſms;</hi> and he joyns <hi>Impoſition of hands with Baptiſm,</hi> becauſe as there were <hi>two Orders of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chumens,</hi> ſo there was a <hi>double ceremony.</hi> For thoſe <hi>without the Church</hi> did not come to Baptiſm before they had made Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Faith: in theſe therefore <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm was wont to precede.</hi> But the <hi>children of the faithful,</hi> becauſe adopted from the womb, and by right of promiſe belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Church, were <hi>baptized Infants;</hi> but their Infancy being paſt, after they were inſtructed in the Faith, they did alſo <hi>offer themſelves to Catechiſm,</hi> which was in them <hi>after Baptiſm;</hi> but then <hi>another ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol was added,</hi> namely <hi>Impoſition of hands. This one place therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly teſtifie,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☜</note> 
                        <hi>that the original of this Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony flowed from the Apoſtles;</hi> though <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards</hi> it was turned into Superſtition, as the World doth commonly degenerate from the <hi>beſt Inſtitutions</hi> to Corruptions. Let us therefore know (ſaith he) that it was <hi>inſtituted by the firſt Authors to be a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Rite of Prayer,</hi> as S.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> 
                        <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo calls
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48306:20"/>it. They deſigned indeed <hi>by this ſymbol to approve the Confeſſion of Faith made by Youth,</hi> but thought of nothing leſs than to rend aſunder the force of Baptiſm. Wherefore the <hi>pure Inſtitution is this day to be retained,</hi> but the <hi>Superſtition to be correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And this place (thus underſtood) makes for the <hi>approbation of Infant Baptiſm:</hi> For why (ſaith he) ſhould that Doctrine be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in <hi>ſome</hi> the <hi>Doctrine of Baptiſms,</hi> and in <hi>others</hi> of <hi>Laying on of hands;</hi> but that theſe later were inſtructed in the Faith af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Baptiſm, ſo that nothing elſe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining but to lay hands upon them?</q>— And again, in his <hi>Book of Inſtitutions;</hi> 
                     <q>This was the <hi>cuſtom of old</hi> (ſaith he) that the <hi>children of Chriſtians,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19. § 4.</note> 
                        <hi>after they were grown up, were preſented before the Biſhop to fulfill that Office which was required of the Adult at their Baptiſm:</hi> for theſe ſate among the Catechumens, till being duly inſtructed in the myſteries of Faith, they were able to make a Confeſſion of the ſame before the Biſhop and People — They were examined by the Biſhop according to a <hi>certain and common form of Catechiſm which they then had;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☞</note> and that this action, which otherwiſe deſervedly ought to be grave and holy, might have the <hi>more reverence and honour,</hi> the Ceremony of <hi>Impoſition of hands was alſo added.</hi> And thus the Child
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48306:20"/>(by his Faith being approved) was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd with a <hi>ſolemn benediction.</hi> Of <hi>this cuſtom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Ancients do often make mention— Such an Impoſition of hands</hi> therefore (ſaith he) as is done barely in the room of Benediction I <hi>commend,</hi> and would this day <hi>reſtored</hi> to a pure uſe—</q> And then again,
<note place="margin">§ 5, &amp;c.</note> after a paſſionate Invective againſt the Corruptions of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> who had defaced the <hi>ſubſtance of the thing,</hi> and inſtead of a <hi>true Confirmation</hi> introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a <hi>feigned Sacrament,</hi> he concludes with moſt earneſt deſires for the <hi>reſtitution</hi> of the primitive Right, in ſuch words as theſe; <q>But I would to God that we <hi>retained the cuſtom</hi> which I intimated to have been among the <hi>Ancients,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">§ 13.</note> before this Abortive Counterfeit of a Sacrament was brought forth.</q> Thus far Mr. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The Apoſtle (ſaith <hi>Beza</hi>) numbers up <hi>five heads of Catechiſm, viz.</hi> the profeſſion of amendment of Life, <hi>(i.e. repentance from dead works:)</hi> the ſumm of <hi>faith concerning God:</hi> the <hi>compendious explication of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that was wont to be delivered to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned,</hi> eſpecially at <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, (i. e.</hi> ſaith he, when they met together to <hi>baptize</hi> Infants or Adult perſons, and alſo when they came toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>impoſe hands</hi> upon any:) the Head of the <hi>reſurrection of the dead</hi> and of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48306:21"/>
                        <hi>future judgment</hi>
                     </q>— And in his <hi>ſhorter notes</hi> he calls them <q>The Heads of Catechiſm, which contain indeed the chief matters of all Evangelical Doctrine, but were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in <hi>few words, and ſummarily</hi> to the unlearned, <hi>viz.</hi> the profeſſion of <hi>repentance and faith towards God.</hi> The Articles of which Doctrine as they are called, were indeed required of thoſe without the Church, at the <hi>appointed days of Baptiſm;</hi> but from the Children of all the Faithful, baptized in their Infancy, <hi>when hands were laid upon them.</hi> Among which Articles <hi>two</hi> (here) are expreſly reckoned up, namely the Reſurrection of the Fleſh, and Eternal Judgment. Thus <hi>Beza.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>This Doctrine,
<note place="margin">Schol. &amp; Obſerv. in loc.</note> ſaith <hi>Piſcator, (viz.</hi> of Repentance from dead works, and Faith towards God) was wont to be delivered to the <hi>Catechumens</hi> before they were <hi>baptized,</hi> or <hi>confirmed in the Chriſtian Faith by the Impoſition of hands</hi>—When Children have been taught the Doctrine of Repentance and Faith, they are to make profeſſion thereof before the Church, and to be <hi>confirmed by the Impoſition of hands.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we think (ſaith he) th s Impoſition of hands to be matter of free obſervance, as having indeed <hi>Apoſtolical example,</hi> but not a <hi>Precept from Chriſt.</hi>
                     </q> (Where we ſee he grants the <hi>Example</hi> roundly enough to be <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> however he would have it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48306:21"/>left <hi>free to conform unto, or to neglect</hi> it.) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (ſaith he) <q>At the firſt ſight there ſeem to be <hi>ſix</hi> Heads of Doctrine diſtinctly reckon'd up; but if one ſhall more accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately weigh them, they may be referr'd to <hi>four,</hi> or to <hi>three:</hi> For the <hi>third</hi> and <hi>fourth (viz.</hi> of Baptiſm and Impoſition of Hands) ſeem not here to be propounded as <hi>peculiar Heads of Doctrine,</hi> but put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt to declare the <hi>Circumſtance of Time,</hi> wherein theſe Fundamentals were wont to be propounded unto Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners, namely, at that time <hi>when the Adult were admitted unto Baptiſm;</hi> and alſo, <hi>when thoſe who were Baptized in their Infancy, and afterwards inſtructed in their Childhood, were wont by the Church, to be confirmed in the Chriſtian Faith, by the Impoſition of Hands.</hi>
                     </q> Thus <hi>Piſcator.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then the <hi>Leiden Divines,</hi> in their <hi>Synop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis purioris Theologiae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Diſ.</hi> 47.</note> tell us to the ſame purpoſe, that, <q>It is probable this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Impoſition of Hands, is referr'd to that <hi>care of the Ancient Church,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Children inſtructed in Catechetical Doctrine, before they were admitted to partake of the Lord's Supper, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Church, to anſwer concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Faith, and commended by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto God, the Rite of <hi>Impoſition of Hands being added</hi> thereunto, which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48306:22"/>was a <hi>Geſture of thoſe that pray and bleſs, even from the time of the Patriarchs.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next, For the <hi>Lutheran Churches,</hi> none can ſpeak better than their famous <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius,</hi> whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſo far honors, as to acknowledge, that he doth of all others <hi>moſt accurately deſcribe the Order of</hi> Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran <hi>Confirmation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Our Divines (ſaith <hi>he</hi>) have often ſhewn,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exam. Concil. Trident. part</hi> 2 <hi>de Confirm.</hi>
                        </note> that the Rite of Confirmation (unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, ſuperſtitious and Anti-ſcriptural Traditions being once remov'd from it) might be uſed piouſly,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Id. Loc. Theolog. part</hi> 3. <hi>de num. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rament.</hi>
                        </note> and to the Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Church, according to the <hi>conſent of Scripture</hi> after this manner, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe who have been <hi>baptized in their Infancy,</hi> (for ſuch now is the State of the Church) when come to years of Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould be diligently <hi>inſtructed in a certain and plain Catechiſm</hi> of the Doctrine of the Church; and when they ſeem com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently to have underſtood the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of it, ſhould afterwards be <hi>preſented to the Biſhop and Church;</hi> and there the Child that was baptized in his Infancy ſhould,</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <q>Be <hi>admoniſhed in a ſhort and plain manner concerning his Baptiſm, (viz. with, what, how, why,</hi> and <hi>into what</hi> he was Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized: What the whole <hi>Trinity</hi> in that Baptiſm <hi>conferr'd</hi> upon him, and <hi>Sealed</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48306:22"/>to him; namely, the Covenant of Peace and Grace; and how there was then made an <hi>Abrenunciatiation</hi> of Satan, a <hi>Profeſſion of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Promiſe of Obedience.)</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <q>The <hi>Child himſelf ſhould before the Church make a proper (or perſonal) and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Confeſſion of this Doctrine and Faith.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <q>He ſhould be queſtion'd <hi>about the chief Heads of Chriſtian Religion;</hi> and where he leſs underſtands any thing, be more rightly inform'd.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <q>He ſhould be put in mind, and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare by this Profeſſion, how he differs from all Heathen, Heretical, Fanatick, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Opinions.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <q>There ſhould be added a grave and ſerious <hi>Exhortation out of the Word of God,</hi> that he would perſevere, and by going forwards, be farther confirmed in the Covenant of Baptiſm, and that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Faith.</q> And then,</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <q>
                        <hi>Publick Prayer ſhould be made for thoſe Children,</hi> that God by his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit would vouchſafe to govern, preſerve, and confirm them in this Profeſſion: <hi>Whereunto without Superſtition, may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Impoſition of Hands.</hi> Nor would that Prayer be <hi>vain:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                        <hi>For it leans upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes concerning the Gift of Perſeverance, and Grace of Confirmation.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:48306:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <q>Such a Rite of Confirmation (ſaith <hi>he</hi>) would contribute very much Profit to the <hi>Education of Youth,</hi> and of the <hi>whole Church;</hi> For it would be agreable both unto <hi>Scripture and purer Antiquity.</hi> Thus <hi>Chemnitius.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But before either <hi>Calvin</hi> or <hi>Luther,</hi> there was one famous <hi>Waldo,</hi> of whom the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> are named, who did more early diſſent from the Corruption of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: And they, in their Confeſſion, exhibited to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> 1504. ſpeak <hi>thus remarkably</hi> of this Rite of Confirmation,</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>We do profeſs with a Faith taken out of the Divine Scriptures,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Confeſs.</hi> Waldenſ. <hi>de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm.</hi>
                        </note> that in the <hi>Times of the Apoſtles</hi> this was obſerved, whoever being come to the Ripeneſs of Years, had not received the promiſed Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, received them afterwards by <hi>Prayer and Impoſition of Hands for the Confirmation of Faith.</hi> The ſame we think alſo of <hi>Infants.</hi> Whoſoever being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, hath come over to the true Faith, which he reſolves to imitate indeed amidſt Adverſities and Contumelies, in that manner, that a new Birth, and Life of Graces, may ſeem diſcovered in his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or Temper: Such an one ought to to be brought, and ſet <hi>before the Biſhop or Prieſt;</hi> where being queſtioned of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48306:23"/>
                        <hi>Truth of Faith,</hi> and the <hi>Divine Commands,</hi> and alſo his <hi>own good Will, Setled Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Works of Truth,</hi> if he ſhall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> that all theſe things are ſo: He is to be confirmed in the Hope of Truth, already attained, and farther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to be <hi>holpen by the Churches Prayers,</hi> that an Increaſe of the Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, may accrue unto him for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment and Warfare of Faith. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by <hi>Impoſition of Hands</hi> to confirm the Promiſes of God and the Truth, in the Power of the Name of the Father, and of his Word, and of the Holy Spirit, let him be <hi>joyn'd to the Churches Communion</hi>— And <hi>again,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apolog. part</hi> 4. <hi>de Baptiſm. puerorum.</hi>
                        </note> in their Apology to the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of</hi> Brandenburgh, 1532. ſpeaking of Children that have been Baptized, they add — When they ſhall have come to <hi>Years of Diſcretion,</hi> and now underſtand the Account of their Faith, and begin to love Chriſt in good earneſt, we bring them to the <hi>Profeſſion of theſe things,</hi> even whatſoever they have attained to by the help of their <hi>Parents,</hi> or <hi>Godfathers,</hi> or by the <hi>Miniſtry of the Church,</hi> that they may <hi>themſelves of their own accord, and moſt freely own and profeſs all theſe things before the whole Church, to their own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, in the celebration of the Rite of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands;</hi> which being done, they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48306:24"/>are <hi>confirmed:</hi> And there is forthwith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them <hi>full Power and Right to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, with the Faithful.</hi>
                     </q> Thus they, who are called <hi>Waldenſes</hi> or <hi>Picardi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to what you have heard from them, give me leave to add <hi>the Form of receiving the Baptized and Catechized Youth among the</hi> Bohemian <hi>Brethren,</hi> who ſometimes go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>ſame</hi> Name (a Remnant of the <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonique Church,</hi> and the Eminent <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Wickleff, Huſs,</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi>) as it is deſcribed to us by their <hi>laſt Biſhop,</hi> the Excellent <hi>Comenius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>The Young ones,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ratio Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip. ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſque Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſtin uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>um</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. p. 46.</note> (ſaith <hi>he</hi>) having been taught the <hi>Heads of Religion</hi> at Home, by their Parents and Sureties, or at School, by their <hi>Maſters,</hi> are <hi>publickly delivered to the care of their Paſtors</hi> in the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>the Receiving of the Lord's Supper,</hi> moſt uſually at the time of <hi>Paſtoral Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> after <hi>this</hi> manner:</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <q>The words of Chriſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all ye that labor,</hi> &amp;c. are read, with a <hi>ſhort Explication</hi> of them.</q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p n="2">2. The <hi>Youth of both Sexes,</hi> appointed thereunto and <hi>preexamined</hi> by the Paſtor, are <hi>placed in order</hi> in the middle of the Church.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Then they are <hi>asked,</hi> whether they will <hi>renew the Covenant they entered into with God at Baptiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:48306:24"/> 4. This being conſented to by them, the <hi>heads of that Covenant are explained according to the form preſcribed by the Apoſtle to Titus, chap.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13. Denying ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, to live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly in this preſent world, looking for the bleſſed hope, &amp;c. And they are <hi>commanded open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before the Church to renounce the World, the Devil, and the Fleſh, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. Next a <hi>profeſſion of the Faith is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> of them, ſo that they all <hi>repete aloud the Apoſtles Creed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p n="6">6. <q>Then, on their <hi>bended Knees,</hi> ſaying <hi>after the Miniſter,</hi> they <hi>pray unto God to forgive the Sins of their Youth, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them by his Holy Spirit, unto all the good purpoſe of his Will;</hi> which alſo the <hi>whole Aſſembly doth, praying for them.</hi>
                     </q> After which Prayers,</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <q>There is declared to theſe young Diſciples, and the whole Church <hi>Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and the Right of the Sons of God, in participating the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>And laſtly, there is added the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Rite of <hi>Impoſition of Hands,</hi> with the <hi>Invocation of the Name of God upon them to ſtrengthen (or confirm) the hope of his Heavenly Grace</hi>— Thus the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Brother-hood, the <hi>moſt exemplary for good Order among all the Reform'd Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48306:25"/>
                  <p> Unto theſe now I could eaſily ſuperadd many other Teſtimonies; but I will cloſe them all with <hi>three or four of our Nation;</hi> and thoſe ſuch as cannot be ſuſpected of caſting any favourable Eye upon a <hi>Brat of Popery or Prelacy,</hi> as ſome have pleaſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally to yoak them.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Hanmer,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> above twenty years ſince, have written each of them, a <hi>Particular Treatiſe upon this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Confirmation:</hi> Finding no ſuch way, it ſeems, to extricate themſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers out of the Confuſions into which the Times were then fallen, as by returning back, <hi>in part, to what had been too raſhly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded together with the Church of</hi> England. And the later of them underſtands <hi>that Text of St.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm.</hi> p. 102. 119.</note> Paul, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. (<q>I put thee in remembrance, that thou ſtir up the Gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on of my Hands) of the <hi>Apoſtolical Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Hands after Baptiſm, for the giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> rather than the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Ordination and Gift.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>William Gouge,</hi> in his Commentary on the <hi>Text,</hi> tells us, that <q>Ordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, wherein Impoſition of Hands was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, were,</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <q>
                        <hi>Bleſſing Children,</hi> by our Saviour, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.16.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <q>
                        <hi>Setting men apart to the publick Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48306:25"/>of Miniſters of the Word,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. and <hi>Deacons, Act.</hi> 6.6.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <q>
                        <hi>Deputing Men to ſome ſpecial Work, Acts</hi> 13.2. And,</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <q>
                        <hi>Confirming ſuch as had been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the Principles of Religion.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>This laſt particular (ſaith he) (meaning Confirmation) is not expreſly ſet down in Scripture, but gathered out of it, by the <hi>Ancient Orthodox Fathers,</hi> and with a <hi>Joint-conſent</hi> afterwards by <hi>moſt Divines,</hi> not <hi>Papiſts</hi> only, but <hi>Proteſtants</hi> alſo.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And of the ſame Judgment thoſe of the <hi>late Aſſembly,</hi> ſo called, who put forth the <hi>Engliſh Annotations,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aſſembl. Annot. in Loc.</note> declare themſelves to be (<q>Laying on of Hands) which (ſay they) is uſually call'd <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which ſtood, 1. In examining thoſe who had been Baptized, what Progreſs they had made in the Doctrine of Chriſtianity: And 2. In praying for them, that God would continue them in the Faith, and give them more Grace, <hi>ſtrengthening them by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Now when the <hi>chief Paſtor or Paſtors</hi> of the Church (ſay they) prayed for them, they <hi>laid their Hands upon them;</hi> whence the <hi>Apoſtolical Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> was called <hi>laying on of Hands.</hi> So St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and ſo <hi>moſt of the Fathers with one Conſent.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48306:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:48306:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:48306:27"/>
                  <p>And here now were a fair occaſion to wonder, that ſo <hi>Reverend and Divine an Aſſembly,</hi> as that was reputed, ſhould ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly <hi>caſt off a thing ſo well eſtabliſhed,</hi> and never ſo much as conſider of it in their <hi>Directory.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vindic. of. Liturgie. p.</hi> 38.</note> 
                     <q>That the defaming and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of this ſo blameleſs and gainful an Order, ſhould be neceſſary or uſeful to any Policy, ſave only, to defend the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil from ſo great a Blow, and to ſuſtain and uphold his Kingdom, I never yet had any Temptation or Motive to ſuſpect or imagine,</q>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr. Ham. L' Eſtrange Alliance of Divine Offices,</hi> p. 262.</note> ſaith our Pious and Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>— And <q>There is not any thing wherein the late pretended <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> amuſe me more than in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, ſaith <hi>another worthy perſon.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nor do I know what Account to make for them, unleſs this may paſs for one, That they <hi>practiced againſt known and avowed Principles;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. C.</hi> p. 174. §. 2.</note> as <hi>T. C.</hi> formerly ſtuck not to aver of Mr. <hi>Calvin himſelf,</hi> That <q>as well as he allowed of Confirmation, he put it out of the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> where he was Paſtor.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this may ſuffice abundantly to have ſpoken concerning the <hi>Scripture Patterns and Grounds,</hi> which we have for this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Appointment, as they are <hi>expounded and handed down to us by moſt unqueſtionable Authorities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:48306:27"/>
                  <p> I paſs on, Thirdly, to the <hi>Ceremony uſed in it,</hi> the <hi>Impoſition of the Biſhop's Hands:</hi> And here I ſhall offer a few words:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of the <hi>Ceremony it ſelf:</hi> And,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of the <hi>Special Miniſter</hi> concerned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Of the <hi>Ceremony it ſelf, Impoſition of Hands,</hi> according to the <hi>Scripture War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> without either <hi>Croſſing, or Annointing,</hi> with <hi>Chriſm made of Oyl and Balſom,</hi> or <hi>boxing on the Ear or Cheek,</hi> as is uſed among the <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This laying on of Hands, is a <hi>moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, unaffected, and Ancient Ceremony of Prayer and Benediction,</hi> as we find it uſed, <hi>firſt, in the Old Teſtament,</hi> and from thence derived into the <hi>New.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Manuum impoſitio ex Hebraeorum more, ad Chriſtianos venit, uſumque habuit in omni Precatione.</hi> Grotius <hi>Not. in</hi> Caſſand. <hi>ad Artic.</hi> 9.— <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Clem. Alex. <hi>Paedag. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>id l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>Under the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> we find it u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>firſt of all, by the Father, in bleſſing of his Children, and admitting them to part of the Inheritance.</hi> Thus when <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſſed <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> the Sons of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> 
                     <q>He laid his Hands upon them and prayed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.14.</q> — And, by way of ſpecial Imitation of his <hi>Paternal Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:48306:28"/>we find it uſed in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> by <hi>our Bleſſed Saviour, St.</hi> Mark 10.16. (which <hi>Grotius</hi> well notes farther, upon St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.13. <q>to have been accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Jewiſh Cuſtom,</hi> it being uſual among them to bring their Children to thoſe that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way eminent for Sanctimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Life,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſt hoc quoque de vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri Sacramento, quo Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſuos ex</hi> Joſeph, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frem <hi>&amp;</hi> Manaſſem, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob. <hi>Capitibus impoſitis &amp; intermutatis manibus benedixerit, &amp;c.</hi> Tertull. <hi>de Baptiſm. c.</hi> 8.</note> to be commended unto God in their Prayers, by <hi>Impoſition of Hands</hi>)—</q> And then afterwards, we find it uſed alſo by the <hi>Apoſtles in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming of Adult perſons that were baptized,</hi> as you have heard before from <hi>Acts</hi> 8. and <hi>Acts</hi> 19.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calvin himſelf,</hi> looks upon <hi>no other My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19. §. 5.</note> under the Impoſition, even of the Apoſtle's Hands; but their ſignifying by this Rite, that they did <hi>commend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto God, as it were by name, him whom they laid their Hands upon.</hi> (Thus they were appointed of Old, <hi>to lay their Hands on the Sacrifice,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caeterae partes lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> adjuvant; manus (propè eſt ut dicam) ipſe loquuntur. In demonſtrandis perſonis atque locis adverbio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum atque pronominum obtinent vicem.</hi> Quintil. Oaat. <hi>l.</hi> 11.</note> &amp;c. And ſo at the <hi>Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Bread and Wine in the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, the Prieſt with us lays his Hands on the Elements.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>And therefore it is ſomewhat ſtrange,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48306:28"/>that in the Heat of his Diſputation againſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> he ſhould ſtart this <hi>idle Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion:</hi> 
                     <q>Whereas the eminent Grace at firſt beſtowed, is ceaſed, <hi>to what purpoſe is Impoſition of Hands yet retained?</hi>
                     </q> Strange, I ſay, it is, whenas himſelf, <hi>more than once,</hi> owneth Impoſition of Hands, for a <hi>Solemn Right of Prayer,</hi> and ſaith, it was uſed by the Apoſtles for <hi>no higher Myſtery</hi> (thoſe are his very words, <hi>non altius ſubeſſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium cogito</hi>—) than to recommend the perſon prayed for particularly unto God. Is not this therefore to make <hi>Prayer for particular Perſons an Impertinency now too,</hi> becauſe miraculous Grace hath ceaſed? As if <hi>no Grace at all</hi> might be now expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe not that <hi>eminent and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Grace</hi> at firſt conferr'd. But ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it is ſtill, when we remember that he alſo <hi>commends and wiſhes for the Reſtitution of ſuch an Impoſition of Hands, as might ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the room of Benediction</hi>— To ſuch an <hi>Inconſiſtency,</hi> and <hi>Forgetfulneſs of themſelves,</hi> are great Men tranſported ſometimes by their own Paſſions.</p>
                  <p>Were <hi>Impoſition of Hands</hi> altogether <hi>need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and of no uſe,</hi> certainly St.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Reaſons againſt <hi>Subſcript. part</hi> 2. p. 85.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> needed not to have taken ſo much pains, as to come on a <hi>fruitleſs</hi> Errand from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Samaria,</hi> to have laid their Hands on them, whom <hi>Philip,</hi> the <hi>Deacon</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:48306:29"/>baptized: For they might as well have (kept at home and) <hi>prayed in</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>for them:</hi> But, to ſhew, that the <hi>other Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Action</hi> might alſo have <hi>due place;</hi> therefore is it, that they did both accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
                  <p>In a Word, this Impoſition of Hands, which we have found to be a fitting and <hi>Scriptural Rite</hi> of Prayer and Benediction, eſpecially, when (as <hi>among us,</hi> it is) accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied <hi>with Expreſs and Solemn Prayer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for the Perſon,</hi> cannot be thought an <hi>inſignificant Ceremony</hi> by any, who have not firſt learn'd to <hi>deride the Holy Scriptures themſelves,</hi> or who have any value left for the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> or any Faith of <hi>God's hearing thoſe devout Prayers,</hi> which are made, and put up to him by his Church for others.</p>
                  <p>It is obſerved by ſome,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick's <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis.</hi>
                     </note> out of <hi>Jewiſh Authors,</hi> that the <hi>Elevation of the Hands of the Prieſt, in the Old Law, at the Bleſſing of the People, was Impoſition of Hands;</hi> and <hi>this Bleſſing call'd the Weapons and Armor of Iſrael</hi>— And that which we read, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Benediction of</hi> Aaron <hi>and his Sons,</hi> Numb. 5.27. <q>They ſhall put my Name on the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and I will bleſs them.</q> 
                     <hi>Junius and Tremelius,</hi> render <hi>(imponentes manus filiis Iſrael, invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabunt nomen meum, &amp; ego benedicam eis)</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48306:29"/>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Laying their Hands on the Children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, they ſhall call on my Name, and I will bleſs them.</hi>
                     </q> Adding farther, in their <hi>Notes on the Place,</hi> for Illuſtration-ſake, <hi>(Duobus ſignis teſtatum facient Populo meo Gratiam meam, quam ego pro fide meâ facturus ſum, Nominis mei invocatione, &amp; manuum ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum impoſitione publicâ &amp; ſolenni)</hi> 
                     <q>By <hi>theſe two Signs,</hi> they ſhall certifie my People of that Grace which I, according to my Promiſe, will conferr upon them, <hi>viz.</hi> by their <hi>calling on my Name,</hi> and by their <hi>publick and ſolemn Impoſition of their own Hands.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now it is worth the Conſidering, that the <hi>Bleſſing of Chriſt's Miniſters,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.29. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
                     <hi>is no leſs Authoritative and Prolifick under the Goſpel, than it was under the Law; (it may be more)</hi> 
                     <q>God having reſerved ſome better thing for us in the Fulneſs of the Bleſſing of the Goſpel of Chriſt, in whom we are bleſſed with all Spiritual Bleſſings.</q> It is a Bleſſing in <hi>God's Name, and by Vertue of his Commiſſion; and Chriſt's Everlaſting Prieſthood, is after the Order of</hi> Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck, who was moſt famous for this Office of Bleſſing; which he accordingly, not only diſchargeth in <hi>Perſon</hi> for us himſelf in Heaven, but <hi>Vertually</hi> upon Earth too, in and by his <hi>Miniſters Benediction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:48306:30"/>
                  <p> Proceed we therefore <hi>Secondly,</hi> to the <hi>Miniſter of this Benediction,</hi> the <hi>Perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, one of Eminency and Superiority in the Church of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Biſhop, from whence it hath familiarly with us been called</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoping.</p>
                  <p>Thus we found it in the <hi>Firſt Patern, Acts</hi> 8. Not <hi>Philip the Deacon,</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John the Apoſtles,</hi> are ſent to confirm the <hi>Samaritans baptized by</hi> Philip—<q>
                        <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> that baptized them, ſaith St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> gave not the Spirit to the Baptized (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) for he had not <hi>Power or Authority ſo to do</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) For this was the Gift of the <hi>Twelve only.</hi> And again, (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) This was the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar of the Apoſtles</hi>—</q> 
                     <hi>Simon Magus</hi> therefore perceiving that Power of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Holy Ghoſt to be in <hi>none but them,</hi> and preſuming, that they which had it, might alſo ſell it, ſought to <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it of them with Money,</hi> as it follows in the Sequel of <hi>that Chapter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear we,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cited by Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> Whitgift, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Hutton.</note> what the Moderate and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Bucer</hi> ſaith on <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <q>The Sign of Impoſition of Hands, <hi>Biſhops only,</hi> did give, and that not without reaſon, For whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Covenant of the Lord is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed</hi> to thoſe that are to be Baptized; or whether they are to be <hi>reconciled</hi> that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48306:30"/>have grievouſly offended; or whether the Miniſters of the Church are to be <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained:</hi> All theſe Miniſterys do beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thoſe to whom the <hi>chief Care</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calvin himſelf</hi> confeſſeth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>prout ante cit.</hi>
                     </note> that the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Uſage, was for the Party to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, to be brought <hi>coram Epiſcopo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Biſhop.</hi> The Church, ſaith St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> ſtill keepeth up the Cuſtom of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands, <hi>in ſuis praepoſitis, in her Chief Governors;</hi> and the Buſineſs was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>à ſolis Epiſcopis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Q.</hi> 44. <hi>in N. I. De Eccleſ. Hier. c.</hi> 2. <hi>In Ep. ad Hebr. Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. adver.</hi> Luciferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. <hi>See Mr. Hooker</hi>'s <hi>Eccleſ. Pol. l.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 262.</note> 
                     <hi>by Biſhops alone</hi>—<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith <hi>Dyonyſius,</hi> and <hi>St. Ambroſe</hi> agreably, that it was to be done, <hi>à Pontificibus, by the High-Prieſts;</hi> and <hi>non niſi per manus Epiſcopis, ſaith St.</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, <hi>By the Hands of the Biſhop only,</hi>—<q>The Riſe of which Obſervation, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from this <hi>Ground,</hi> (ſaith he) that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Aſcenſion of our Lord, the Holy Ghoſt came down on the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and it obtained in many places, as he adds, not ſo much by the <hi>neceſſity of a Law,</hi> as from a certain <hi>congruity and fitneſs, to honor Prelacy with ſuch Preheminencies,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Safety of the Church, depends on the Dignity of her Superiors, to whom, if ſome</hi> Eminent Offices of Power ſhould not be given, there would be as many Schiſms in the Church, as Prieſts— with us,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48306:31"/>ſaith he <hi>elſewhere, Biſhops hold the place of the Apoſtles.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ep. ad</hi> Marcell. <hi>Id. in</hi> Pſal. 45.</note> And again, For the <hi>Fathers, the Apoſtles,</hi> we have their <hi>Sons, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi>— And in his Comment on the <hi>Firſt of</hi> S. <hi>Mark,</hi>
                     </q> (if that be his) <q>That which is perfected by the <hi>Bridegroom,</hi> ſaith he, is begun by the <hi>Paranymph;</hi> whence <hi>Catechumens (incipiunt per Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotem, &amp; chriſmantur per Epiſcopum) begin by the Prieſt, and are confirmed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>They are therefore to be condemned certainly of <hi>groſs Partiality</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit. of Confirm.</hi> p. 51.</note> who bluſh not to ſay, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops out of <hi>Pride</hi> have appropriated this unto themſelves.</p>
                  <p>May all the Miniſters of Chriſt orderly diſcharge their <hi>proper Duties,</hi> without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>envying</hi> or <hi>invading</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Rights and Priviledges of any whom God hath placed over them.</p>
                  <p>I will not diſpute, what <hi>might poſſibly be allowed,</hi> in Caſes of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> (which excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, as we ſay, what it <hi>compells</hi> unto) and were, methinks, much to be <hi>wiſhed for in larger Dioceſes,</hi> concerning a <hi>Delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Power,</hi> by way of <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> for the more effectual and conſtant expediteing of this good Performance; as ſeems to have been permitted to the <hi>Antient Chore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48306:31"/>&amp;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Rural Biſhops,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melii An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. <hi>in ep.</hi> 13. D. Cyprian. <hi>Dr.</hi> H. diſſert. de Epiſc. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8. Epiſcopus, vel ejus Suffraganeus <hi>can.</hi> 60. R. Jacobi.</note> 
                     <hi>Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and Viſitors conſtituted by the Biſhop of the City.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But it is certainly moſt fitting for <hi>thoſe</hi> to impart this Solemn Benediction, who are of <hi>chiefeſt Note and Eminence</hi> in the Church; and that by the <hi>Analogy of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Rule, Heb.</hi> 7.7. <q>Without Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction the leſs is Bleſſed,</q> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of the better, or greater.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Come we next to the <hi>Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Perſons to be confirmed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such they muſt be,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non 40.</note> who are <hi>baptized and inſtructed in the Catechiſm of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and <hi>come to years of Diſcretion,</hi> in ſome competent Degree to underſtand the ſame, and give an actual and deliberate Aſſent thereunto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Buxtorf</hi> obſerves in the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Synag. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daic.</note> that when the Child was come to be <hi>Thirteen years</hi> of Age, the Father, having taught him the Principles of his Religion, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him in a Sacred Aſſembly, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelf to become <hi>Bar-mitzvah, a Son of the Precept,</hi> that is, as they explain it, ſuch an one, who <hi>takes upon himſelf Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Law, from thence forward, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for his own Sins;</hi> and hereupon
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48306:32"/>
                     <hi>Prayer</hi> was alſo made for his Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Our <hi>Church-Catechiſm</hi> is call'd (as I have ſuggeſted before) <q>
                        <hi>An Inſtruction to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of every perſon, before he be brought to be confirmed by the Biſhop:</hi> which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be done, ſo ſoon as he can ſay <hi>the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and the Ten Commandments in the Vulgar Tongue,</hi> and be <hi>farther inſtructed in the Church Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, ſet forth for that purpoſe</hi>— as 'tis expreſs'd in the <hi>Office of Publick Baptiſm.</hi>
                     </q> And the <hi>Title of this Office it ſelf, in our Service-book,</hi> is, <q>The <hi>Order of Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or laying on of Hands upon thoſe that are baptized, and come to Years of Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>— The <hi>Preface</hi> whereunto is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remarkable.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>To the end that Confirmation may be miniſtred to the more edifying of ſuch as ſhall receive it,
<note place="margin">Order of Confirm.</note> the Church hath thought good to Order. That <hi>none hereafter ſhall be confirmed, but ſuch as can ſay the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and can alſo anſwer to ſuch other Queſtions, as in the ſhort Catechiſm are contained.</hi> Which <hi>Order</hi> is very conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to obſerved, to the end, that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren being now come to <hi>Years of Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and having <hi>learn'd what their Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and Godmothers promiſed for them in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48306:32"/>Baptiſm,</hi> they may with their <hi>own Mouth and Conſent, openly before the Church, rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and confirm the ſame;</hi> and alſo promiſe, that by the Grace of God, they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour <hi>themſelves faithfully to obſerve ſuch things,</hi> as they, by their <hi>own Confeſſion,</hi> have aſſented to.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this Preface is openly <hi>to be read at that time</hi> to the Expectants:
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is appointed to <hi>ask each of them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Do ye here, in the preſence of God, and of this Congregation, <hi>renew the ſolemn Promiſe and Vow that was made in your Name at your Baptiſm, ratifying and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the ſame in your own perſons, and acknowledging your ſelves bound to believe, and do all thoſe things which your God-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and God-mothers then undertook for you?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which Queſtion, <hi>every one is to anſwer audably in the Affirmative,</hi> 'I do— And thereupon the Biſhop proceeds unto <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Benediction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Add hereunto,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Can.</hi> 59. &amp; 61. <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bric's</hi> at the end of the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm.</note> that the <hi>Canons of our Church</hi> enjoyn a ſpecial Care upon all <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> to <hi>prepare thoſe under their Charge hereunto,</hi> and <hi>to ſee that none be preſented, but ſuch as ſhall be thus fitted for it</hi>— And our <hi>Right Reverend Dioceſan</hi> hath declared, that <q>as <hi>de jure</hi> he <hi>cannot;</hi> ſo <hi>de facto</hi> he <hi>will</hi> not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48306:33"/>confirm any,
<note place="margin">Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement in the end of his Book of Articles</note> ſave ſuch only, who have been duly catechized, and by their <hi>Paſtor's Teſtimony,</hi> have attained ſuch a meaſure of Knowledge of the Principles of Chriſtian Religion, as may render them capable of it.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aquinas</hi> indeed determines, that the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Confirmation,</hi> as he calls it, ought to be exhibited in <hi>common to all that are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Part 3. Q. 72. Artic. 8.</note> and at all times. <q>The bodily Age, (ſaith he) doth not prejudice the Soul; and even Children, dying confirmed, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the greater Glory, as here they do the greater Grace.</q>
                     <note place="margin">L. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram.</note> And <hi>Contarenus</hi> grounds the Cuſtom of giving it to Infants upon <hi>his Authority</hi>— But <hi>grave men among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves miſlike this Practice.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Conſult. ad Artic.</hi> 9.</note> 
                     <q>I ſee, ſaith <hi>Caſſander,</hi> that it doth not diſpleaſe good men of both ſides, that the uſe of it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd till ſome <hi>Growth of Age</hi>— And ſo the <hi>Roman Catechiſm now requires.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>The truth is, the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility and Benefit of this Sacred Inſtitution exacts all this.</hi> Some competent Growth and Underſtanding in the Party confirmed, Heed and Diligence in his Prae-inſtruction, and all Gravity, and Seriouſneſs in the whole Adminiſtration. (<q>And to the intent that no man ſhould think that any Detriment ſhould come to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, by deferring their Confirmation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to years of Diſcretion, our Church hath
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48306:33"/>declared it for a <hi>Truth certain by God's Word,</hi> That Children being baptized, have all things neceſſary for their Salvation, and dying before they commit actual Sin, are undoubtedly ſaved.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let me therefore beſeech thoſe, who ſhall come at any time upon this Holy Errand, to ponder well, and conſider with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>of what weight and moment the matter is they are going about, what they are obliged to do, and what the Bleſſing is they hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thereupon</hi>— Their Buſineſs, in ſhort, is to declare, that they are not <hi>aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>glory in his Croſs;</hi> to <hi>profeſs themſelves upon choice, and in good earneſt Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>reſolved Diſciples, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Souldiers of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote themſelves entirely to his Faith and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice;</hi> to <hi>take the ſolemn Vow and Promiſe, made formerly in their Names, by their Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, upon themſelves,</hi> that is, to <hi>vow Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from dead Works and Faith towards God;</hi> to <hi>renounce the Devil, the World and the Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>give up themſelves to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and Obedience of the Goſpel</hi>— This is the Work they come about; and then their Reward is, <hi>ſo doing, to participate in the Prayers of the Church, and the Bleſſing of the Biſhop,</hi> to be <hi>promoted to an higher Form in the School of Chriſt,</hi> among an <hi>higher Rank of Profeſſors,</hi> and admitted to all the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48306:34"/>af Adult and Compleat Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now therefore, in the laſt place, I need not to ſay much more, concerning the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of this whole Action,</hi> which all along <hi>ſpeaks for it ſelf,</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of accordingly I have ſuggeſted a <hi>competent Account</hi> already, in treating of the parts of it. The fewer words therefore ſhall here ſuffice, and I will <hi>little more than name the particulars,</hi> which otherwiſe I ſhould have enlarged upon.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This would utterly <hi>enervate the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts Plea, for Re-baptizing thoſe who were before baptized in their Infancy;</hi> did they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one at their <hi>Confirmation</hi> thus expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely take upon themſelves, what was then <hi>promiſed and undertaken</hi> in their Name, and ſo give up themſelves afreſh to God and his Church. And it is, you know, <hi>part of the Charge which we leave with God-fathers, and God-mothers at the Font,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Office of Public Baptiſm.</note> to bring them, when prepared, unto the Biſhop thus to do.</p>
                  <p>Nor is this, as <hi>ſome</hi> have ſurmized, any Imputation to their <hi>Baptiſm, as imperfect in it ſelf,</hi> but a Supply only to the <hi>Imperfection of their State,</hi> who were Baptized in their Infancy, with a <hi>legitimate and true Baptiſm,</hi> by the <hi>ſolemn renewing of the Anſwer, or Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation of a good Conſcience towards God,</hi> which ought frequently to be repeated
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48306:34"/>throughout our whole Life.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Praef. ad. Paraph. in Evang. S.</hi> Matth.</note> 
                     <hi>Repraeſentatio priſtini Baptiſmi,</hi> as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> calls it.</p>
                  <p>And <q>Whether the ſolemn Baptizing of all Infants, though the Children of preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſtian Parents, throughout this Kingdom, <hi>Without ſolemn Aſtipulation,</hi> that they ſhall at Years of Diſcretion, <hi>perſonally ratifie</hi> their Vow in Baptiſm in Publick, in ſuch manner as <hi>the Church requires,</hi> be not rather more <hi>Lawful than Expedient,</hi> I leave with all Submiſſion,
<note place="margin">On the Creed. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 50.</note> to the Conſideration of <hi>Higher Powers,</hi>
                     </q> ſaith the Learned, Pious, and Reverend Dr. <hi>Jackson.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. This would <hi>ſupercede the new modell'd Examinations, ſet on foot by Private Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, before the Admiſſion of Perſons to the Bleſſed Sacrament of the Lord's Supper,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Lay-Elders,</hi> in Conjunction with Preſbyters, or by <hi>Popular Congregations;</hi> and wholly ſilence the many fierce and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy <hi>Feuds</hi> and <hi>Controverſies,</hi> which have been moved on that occaſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It would extreamly <hi>quicken and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Endeavors of all that are concern'd among us in the Prae-inſtruction of Youth; and whet the Learners alſo to a greater Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Induſtry,</hi> and prove <hi>a mighty Eaſe and Satisfaction to the Minds of thoſe who have undertaken in their Names at Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. It would <hi>very much conduce to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending, and endearing of God's Miniſters,</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:48306:35"/>the <hi>Biſhops of the Church, to the Affections of the People, by and from whom they and theirs partake of ſo great a benefit;</hi> ſo as to oblige them (if any thing can do it) never to lift up their <hi>Hand,</hi> or ſo much as open their <hi>Mouth</hi> againſt them; never to return them <hi>Evil for Good,</hi> and requite their <hi>Bleſſings</hi> with <hi>Curſes and Reproaches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. It would highly promote <hi>the Truth and Power of Godlineſs and Religion,</hi> ſo much talk'd of. It would <hi>bring good Inſtructions to ſome hopeful Effect and Iſſue;</hi> and put <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sinner among us, who is not alſo paſt Shame, to bluſh and hang down the Head upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that good Confeſſion, which he himſelf had ſo openly made before many Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See Dr. Patrick<hi>'s</hi> excellent and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate Exhortation unto Confirmation. <hi>Aqua Genitalis Uſe</hi> 4. and the Appendix.</note> 
                     <hi>and yet ſo notoriouſly violated and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With what Face could he devote himſelf to <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Impiety,</hi> who, before God, and his Elect Angels, the Biſhop, and an Aſſembly of Chriſtians, hath <hi>perſonally vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and promiſed the Belief of the Chriſtian Faith and Obedience unto all God's Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments?</hi> And <hi>with ſuch a grave Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, renounced the Devil and all his Works,</hi> &amp;c. He hath the Argument of <hi>Common Juſtice and Honeſty, from henceforth admoniſhing of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48306:35"/>him continually to be as good as his Word;</hi> to take heed of the crying Sin of <hi>Perjury, ſuch an aggravated Perjury</hi> eſpecially, as this is, a <hi>Sacrilegious Perjury.</hi> He hath <hi>many to riſe up in Judgment againſt him upon Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> He hath ſuch-like Thoughts as theſe to accompany him wherever he goes, that if he fails in this <hi>vowed Duty,</hi> he muſt at laſt <hi>witneſs againſt himſelf,</hi> be <hi>condemned out of his own Mouth,</hi> and <hi>left without an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy;</hi> and if he ſhall preſume to live in a <hi>Courſe, contradictory to this Holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> he can expect nothing but <hi>that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Doom,</hi> which with ſo many repeated Woes is threatned unto <hi>Hypocrites</hi> in the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Nor yet is this <hi>all the Help,</hi> which it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes unto Piety and Religion: But the the <hi>very confirming of our Sacred Vows and Reſolutions, fortifies and arms us againſt Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations:</hi> And while we thus <hi>renew our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes unto God,</hi> we <hi>take his Yoak upon our Necks,</hi> and <hi>come under the Bond of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> And he that <hi>heareth Prayers,</hi> to be ſure, will never ſtop his gracious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Ears <hi>againſt thoſe, who, upon ſo good a Deſign, call upon him; or deny his Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Bleſſing unto thoſe, who are both deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and prepared thus to receive it;</hi> whom therefore his Miniſters, by Vertue of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48306:36"/>and Commiſſion from him, <hi>do bleſs in his name</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">It is ſomewhat obſervable that <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> (St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Contemporary) notes of <hi>Novatian,</hi> that he <hi>therefore fell into Hereſie for want of Epiſcopal Confirmation. Vide</hi> Pamelii <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in D.</hi> Cyprian. Ep. 72.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>To draw towards a <hi>Concluſion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Circa A. D.</hi> 312.</note> remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are the words of <hi>Melchiades,</hi> in his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Biſhops of</hi> Spain,
<note place="margin">Diſcourſe of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>p.</hi> 73.74.</note> concerning the <hi>Neceſſity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of this Holy Rite.</hi> Take them in <hi>Biſhop Taylor's Tranſlation</hi>— Firſt he ſtarts an <hi>Objection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>What does the Myſtery of <hi>Confirmation</hi> profit me, after the Myſtery of <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly we did not receive all in our <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> if <hi>after that Lavatory we want ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> of another kind</q>— And then he ſub-joyns this Anſwer to it— <q>Let your Charity attend (ſaith he) as the Military Order requires, that when the <hi>General</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters a Souldier into his Liſt, he doth not only <hi>mark</hi> him, but furniſh him with <hi>Arms to the Battel;</hi> ſo, in him that is <hi>baptized, this Bleſſing is his Ammunition.</hi> You have given (Chriſt) a <hi>Souldier;</hi> Give him alſo <hi>Weapons.</hi> And, if a Father give a <hi>Great Eſtate</hi> to his Son, what will it profit, if he does not take care to provide a <hi>Tutor</hi> for him? Therefore the Holy Spirit (giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en at Confirmation) is the <hi>Guardian of our Regeneration</hi> in Chriſt;</q> he is the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48306:36"/>
                     <hi>Comforter,</hi> and he is the Defender, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame we meet with in <hi>Euſebius E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſenus;</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Circa A.D.</hi> 360.</note> or, as ſome conceive, <hi>Eucheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Lugdunenſis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">‖ <hi>Circa A.D.</hi> 450.</note> whom I before quoted for <hi>deducing this Obſervance from the Deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt, at</hi> Pentecoſt— After which it follows— <q>But becauſe we have ſaid, that Impoſition of Hands, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, may confer ſomewhat upon him, who is already <hi>regenerate</hi> in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dr.</hi> H. <hi>de Confirm. c.</hi> 6. §. 8.</note> ſome perhaps thinks with himſelf, what doth the Miniſtry of him that confirmeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit me after the Myſtery of Baptiſm?</q> — There is the <hi>Objection.</hi> To which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, <hi>juſt as</hi> Melchiades <hi>did.</hi> 
                     <q>As a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, whomſoever he hath taken into the Liſt of his Souldiers, doth not only ſet a <hi>Mark</hi> upon him, when firſt received; but alſo <hi>furniſheth him, when he is to fight, with fitting Weapons:</hi> So this Benediction is to the <hi>Baptized Perſon</hi> his Accoutrement <hi>for Fight.</hi> You have admitted a <hi>Souldier,</hi> give him alſo the <hi>Helps of Warfare</hi>—</q> And then he <hi>adds, by way of farther Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> —<q>The Holy Ghoſt, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth with a <hi>Saving Illapſe,</hi> on the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> beſtows at the <hi>Font</hi> a Fulneſs, in Order to <hi>Innocency;</hi> and in <hi>Confirmation,</hi> gives a <hi>Supply of Grace,</hi> in order unto <hi>Growth.</hi>
                     </q> In <hi>Baptiſm</hi> we are regenerated unto Life; after <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> we
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48306:37"/>
                     <q>
                        <hi>confirmed to fight.</hi> In <hi>Baptiſm</hi> we are <hi>waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Carranza <hi>Sum. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</hi> Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiades <hi>Papae.</hi>
                        </note> after <hi>Baptiſm</hi> we are <hi>ſtrengthened— Regeneration it ſelf, ſaveth thoſe that are forthwith upon it to he received in the Peace of the Bleſſed Age to come. Confirmation arms and prepares thoſe, who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to the Combates and Fights of this World.</hi> And therefore, <hi>before the Deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt, the Apoſtles are afrighted to a Denyal,</hi> but <hi>after his Viſitation,</hi> are <hi>armed with Contempt of Death unto Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will here annex what the excellent <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> Taylor <hi>himſelf,</hi> ſaith, concerning the <hi>Graces and Bleſſings, conſequent to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Reception and due Miniſtry of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> becauſe they may ſerve for a <hi>beneficial Recapitulation of what hath been already diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <q>Confirmation (ſaith he) is the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation and Perfection,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. §. 6.</note> 
                        <hi>the Corroborati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Strength of Baptiſm, and baptiſmal Grace:</hi> For in <hi>Baptiſm we undertake to do our Duty;</hi> but in <hi>Confirmation,</hi> we receive <hi>further Strength</hi> to do it. In <hi>Baptiſm, others promiſe for us;</hi> in Confirmation we <hi>undertake for our ſelves:</hi> We <hi>eaſe our God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and God-mothers of their Burthen,</hi> and <hi>take it upon our own Shoulders,</hi> together with the <hi>Advantage of the Prayers of the Biſhop, and all the Church on our behalf.</hi> In
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48306:37"/>Baptiſm, we give up our <hi>Names to Chriſt;</hi> but in Confirmation, we <hi>put our Seal to the Profeſſion,</hi> and <hi>God puts his Seal to the Promiſe,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <q>In Confirmation, we <hi>receive the Holy Ghoſt as the Earneſt of our Inheritance,</hi> as <hi>the Seal of our Salvation</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſaith <hi>Greg. Nazianzen,</hi> we therefore call it a Seal or Signature, as being a <hi>Guard and Cuſtody to us,</hi> and a <hi>Sign of the Lord's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over us.</hi> The Confirmed Perſon, is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>a Sheep that is mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> which Thieves do not ſo eaſily ſteal and carry away. Remember,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Comment. in</hi> Cant.</note> ſaith <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi> that Holy Myſtagogy, in which the initiated, after <hi>renouncing that Tyrant</hi> (the Devil, with his Works) and the <hi>Confeſſion of the True King</hi> (Jeſus Chriſt) have received the <hi>Chriſm of Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction like a Royal Signature;</hi> and by that Unction, as in a Type or Shadow, <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Grace of the moſt Holy Spirit,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>To conclude this Enquiry (ſaith he) the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>promiſed to all men to profit withal.</hi> That's plain Scripture: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, or Prayer, and Impoſition of the Biſhop's Hands, is the <hi>Solemnity and Rite uſed in Scripture for the conveying of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and the Effect is felt in all the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, and Changes of the Soul.</hi> And he,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48306:38"/>that denies theſe things, hath not <hi>Faith,</hi> nor the <hi>True Notices of Religion,</hi> or the <hi>Spirit of Chriſtianity.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will only add this now in the <hi>cloſe</hi> of all, by way of <hi>Admonition;</hi> that we are all concern'd <hi>not to diſgrace ſo well grounded Principles, by an unſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>table practice,</hi> leſt we furniſh our Adverſaries with the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence againſt Confirmation, as it is happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſettled in our Church-Conſtitutions, which <hi>Calvin</hi> urged againſt that of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts (ſcilicet dum ità licenter contemni pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuntur,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19. §. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>tacitè fatentur, non tanti eſſe, quanti venditant)</hi> 
                     <q>That <hi>while we ſuffer it to be ſo profanely contemned, we do ſilently confeſs, that it is not of ſo great a Value, as otherwiſe we give forth, and atteſt it to be.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>There is no cauſe we ſhould doubt of the Benefit (ſaith our Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi>) but ſurely great cauſe to make Complaint of the deep Neglect of this Chriſtian Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ. Pol. l.</hi> 5.</note> 
                        <hi>almoſt with all them to whom by right of their Place and Calling, the ſame belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> Let them not take it in evil part (ſaith he) the thing is true, <hi>Their ſmall regard hereunto, hath done harm to the Church of God.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☞</note> That which <hi>Error</hi> raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uttereth in diſgrace of good things, may peradventure be ſpunged out, when the Print of thoſe Evils, which are grown through Neglect, will remain behind.</p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:48306:38"/>
                     <p> There is no default or defect (ſaith profound Dr.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>L.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 50</note> 
                        <hi>Jackſon</hi>) in the Church of <hi>England's Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Laws,</hi> concerning <hi>Baptiſm</hi> or <hi>Confirmation</hi> of ſuch as have been Baptized in their Infancy. But I dare not avouch ſo much for juſtifying the <hi>men unto whom the Execution of thoſe Laws is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially commended,</hi> whether they be of Lower, or Higher, or of the Higheſt Rank, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In this point, who can deny</hi> (ſaith the Pious and Reverend Dr.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>De Confir.</hi> p. 81.</note> 
                        <hi>Hammond</hi>) <hi>but there is fit place for Reformation?</hi> — And his Worthy and Learned Friend, Dr. <hi>Henchman,</hi> the Late Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> (but when he wrote of <hi>Salisbury</hi>) in his <hi>praeliminary Diſcourſe to that excellent Treatiſe of his, de Confirmatione,</hi> urgeth the matter home upon us</p>
                     <p>If theſe things (ſaith he) at laſt,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Praelim. Diatrib.</hi> H. S.</note> take not hold of our minds, where is the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline for ſo many Years, deſigned and thought on,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">☜</note> 
                        <hi>and during the Oppreſſion and Rage of the late Tyranny, promiſed, if ever good day ſhould ſhine upon us?</hi> Behold, our Moſt Gracious and Merciful God, hath commanded his Sun to ſhine bright a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain upon our Iſland, and <hi>calmed the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt</hi> which toſs'd our Ship, and now <hi>calls for the performance of our Vow unto him,</hi> the <hi>Vow which we made when we were in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48306:39"/>Trouble.</hi> Let us offer unto him <hi>this Holy and ſincere Worſhip,</hi> whilſt we every one readily diſcharge our reſpective <hi>Duties</hi> in this particular.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Which that we may <hi>all</hi> do, God of his Infinite Mercy, grant, for Chriſt his Sake, to whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, (that <hi>Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> in whoſe name we were <hi>baptized,</hi> and <hi>whoſe Diſciples, at our Confirmation, we own and profeſs our ſelves to be</hi>) be aſcribed by us, as is moſt due, all Honor, Glory, Praiſe and Adoration, now and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="appendix">
                  <head>APPENDIX.</head>
                  <p>ALthough I have ſaid enough to <hi>obviate</hi> moſt of the <hi>Common Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections</hi> againſt this Sacred Rite of Confirmation, in the fore-going Pages; yet becauſe I find them <hi>all epitomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the ſtouteſt Champion of the Old Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> (whoſe Eructations have been lick'd up by the New, as <hi>Homer</hi>'s were by the Succeeding Poets) and as <hi>full an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:48306:39"/>to them, though <hi>compendious and Iro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical,</hi> in our Excellent <hi>Hooker,</hi> I will take the pains here for the Reader's Benefit to <hi>tranſcribe both in Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>T. C.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reply to Anſwer to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monit. <hi>p.</hi> 160.</note> In his Reply to the moſt Reverend Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <q>Tell me, why there ſhould be any ſuch Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in the Church, being <hi>brought in by the feigned Decretal Epiſtles of Popes;</hi> (But this is <hi>retracted</hi> by him, <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 232. That it is <hi>Ancienter</hi> than the feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Decretal Epiſtles I yield unto) and <hi>no one Title thereof being once found in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> and ſeeing it hath been <hi>ſo horribly abuſed,</hi> and not neceſſary, why ought it not to be utterly aboliſhed? And Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, This Confirmation hath many <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous points</hi> in it. The <hi>Firſt ſtep of Popery</hi> in this Confirmation, is the <hi>laying on of Hands upon the Head of the Child,</hi> whereby the Opinion of it, that it is a <hi>Sacrament</hi> is confirmed; eſpecially, whenas the Prayer doth ſay, that it is <hi>done according to the Example of the Apoſtles;</hi> which is a <hi>manifeſt untruth,</hi> and taken indeed from the <hi>Popiſh Confirmation.</hi> The Second is, for that the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as he is call'd, muſt be the <hi>only Miniſter</hi> of it, whereby the Popiſh Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which eſteemeth it <hi>above Baptiſm,</hi> is confirmed: For while Baptiſm may be miniſtred of the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48306:40"/>but only of the Biſhop, there is great Cauſe of Suſpicion given to think, <hi>that Baptiſm is not ſo ſerious a thing as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation;</hi> ſeeing this was one of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Reaſons, whereby that wicked O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion was eſtabliſhed in Popery. I do not here ſpeak of the <hi>Inconvenience,</hi> that men are conſtrained with Charges to bring their Children oftentimes <hi>half- a ſcore miles</hi> for that, which if it were needful, might be as well done at Home in their own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes. The Third is, for that the <hi>Book</hi> ſaith, a Cauſe of uſing Confirmation, is, <hi>That by Impoſition of Hands and Prayer, the Children may receive Strength and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt all Temptations;</hi> whereas there is no <hi>Promiſe,</hi> that by the laying on of Hands upon Children any ſuch Gift ſhall be given: And it maintaineth the <hi>Popiſh Diſtinction,</hi> that the Spirit of God is giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en at <hi>Baptiſm</hi> unto <hi>Remiſſion of Sins,</hi> and in <hi>Confirmation</hi> unto <hi>Strength.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hear we now Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> in few, but weighty words, cloſing up his <hi>Nervous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> about Confirmation, with a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Retort to <hi>all theſe</hi> Objections.</p>
                  <p>(<q>Thus much generally ſpoken,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ic. l.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 263.</note> may ſerve for <hi>Anſwer</hi> to their Demands, that require us to tell them <hi>why there ſhould be any ſuch Confirmation in the Church,</hi> ſeeing we are not ignorant, how earneſtly they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48306:40"/>have <hi>proteſted againſt it;</hi> and how <hi>directly</hi> (although <hi>untruly,</hi> for ſo they are content to acknowledge) it hath by ſome of them been ſaid to be firſt brought <hi>in by the feigned Decretal Epiſtles of the Popes:</hi> Or why it ſhould not utterly be aboliſhed, ſeeing that <hi>no one Title thereof can be once found in the whole Scriptures,</hi> except the <hi>Epiſtle to the</hi> Hebrews <hi>be Scripture,</hi> ch. 6.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— And again, ſeeing, that how free ſoever it be now from abuſe, if we look back to times paſt (which wiſe men do always more reſpect than the preſent) it hath <hi>been abuſed</hi> (as what good thing hath not?) and is found at length no ſuch profitable Ceremony, as the whole <hi>ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church of Chriſt for the ſpace of theſe ſixteen Hundred Years, hath, through want of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience imagined.</hi> Laſt of all, ſeeing alſo, beſides the <hi>Cruelty,</hi> which is ſhew'd towards poor Country People, who are fain ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to let the Plow ſtand ſtill, and with incredible weariſome Toyl of their feeble Bodies, to wander over Mountains, and through Woods, it may be now and then, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſs than a <hi>whole half-ſcore miles,</hi> for a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Bleſſing, which if it were needful, might as well be done at home in their own Pariſhes, rather than they to purchaſe it with ſo great Loſs and intollerable pain.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48306:41"/>There are, they ſay, in Confirmation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>this, three terrible Points.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>The Firſt is <hi>laying on of Hands, with pretence that the ſame is done to the Example of the Apoſtles,</hi> which is not only as they ſuppoſe, a <hi>manifeſt untruth</hi> (For all the World doth know, that the <hi>Apoſtles did never after Baptiſm lay Hands on any:</hi> And therefore <hi>S.</hi> Luke <hi>who ſaith they did, Acts</hi> 8. <hi>and</hi> 19. <hi>was much deceived</hi>) but farther alſo, we thereby teach men to think Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands a Sacrament; belike, becauſe it is a <hi>Principle, ingrafted by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Light of Nature, in the minds of men, that all things done by Apoſtolick Example, muſt needs be Sacraments.</hi> (And yet the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> too, is ſometimes uſed by the Fathers in a <hi>very large Extent;</hi> and <hi>Bucer</hi> calls this a <hi>Sacramental Rite.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Second high point of Danger, is, that by tying Confirmation to the <hi>Biſhop alone,</hi> there is great cauſe of Suſpicion given to think, that <hi>Baptiſm is not ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a thing as Confirmation:</hi> For will any man think that a <hi>Velvet Coat, is of no more price than a Linnen Coife,</hi> knowing the one to be an <hi>Ordinary Garment,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Ornament which only Sergeants at Law wear?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Finally, to draw to an end of Perils, the laſt and the weightieſt hazzard, is,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48306:41"/>where the Book it ſelf doth ſay, that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, by Impoſition of Hands, and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, may receive <hi>ſtrength againſt all Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi> This Speech, as a Two-edged Sword, doth both ways dangerouſly wound: Partly, becauſe it aſcribeth <hi>Grace to Impoſition of Hands,</hi> whereby we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble no more to aſſure our ſelves in the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of any Promiſe from God, that his Heavenly Grace ſhall be given, than the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> was, that himſelf ſhould obtain Grace, by the <hi>bowing of his Knees to God, Epheſ.</hi> 3.14. And partly becauſe by uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very word <hi>Strength</hi> in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a word ſo apt to ſpread Infection, we maintain, with <hi>Popiſh Evangeliſts (John</hi> 20.22. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8.) an old forlorn Diſtinction of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt beſtowed upon Chriſt's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles before his Aſcenſion into Heaven,</hi> and <hi>augmented upon them afterwards;</hi> a Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Grace infuſed into Chriſtian Men by degrees, planted in them at firſt by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and after that, cheriſhed, watered, and</hi> (be it ſpoken without Offence) <hi>ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> as by <hi>other vertuous Offices,</hi> which Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and True Religion teacheth, even ſo <hi>by this very ſpecial Benediction,</hi> whereof we ſpeak, the Rite or Ceremony of Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.)</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>And now, by way of <hi>Over-plus,</hi> I ſhall eaſily obtain pardon for tranſlating to the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48306:42"/>uſe of my Country-men <hi>theſe admirable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the Reverend Dr.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>De Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat. Praef.</hi> §. 10. <hi>item c.</hi> 11. §. 6. <hi>ſubſec.</hi> 8.</note> Hammond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>Undoubtedly were <hi>theſe</hi> things, as they are holily and wiſely <hi>ordain'd</hi> in the Church of Chriſt, (either by the <hi>Apoſtles themſelves,</hi> or after their Patern, by Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical men, the Succeſſors of their Chair and Power) ſo alſo piouſly, reverently, and conſtantly applied by Prelates, <hi>other Weapons of the Churches Warfare, being in their Place and Order call'd in for Help,</hi> as often as there is need; (that is to ſay, more particularly, and diſtinctly, if care were taken by the <hi>Rectors</hi> or <hi>Curates of all Pariſhes,</hi> to bring thoſe who have been Baptized in their Infancy, and afterwards inſtructed in the Catechiſm (which is a plain <hi>Explication of the Baptiſmal Vow and Heads of Faith)</hi> to the Biſhop, no leſs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent for his Sanctity than Honor; and they admitted <hi>hereupon, by the Impoſition of his Hand and Benediction, as alſo, by his Paternal Monition and Threatning, to a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Confirmation of the Profeſſion and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renunciation made in their Names at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm;</hi> being upon <hi>theſe Terms only</hi> permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>approach the Lord's Table;</hi> and to be <hi>driven from thence,</hi> bound by the Power of the Keys, and interdicted the Priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of <hi>Diſciples, as often as they are found in a Crime,</hi> or <hi>manifeſtly guilty of voluntary Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion;</hi>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:48306:42"/>and to be <hi>redeemed from this Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, by the Plank of genuine and ſolid Repentance only:</hi> If, I ſay we Chriſtians were accuſtomed to ſerve and go forward in the Camp of Chriſt, by <hi>this ſevere, but not tetrical Law,</hi> fitted not ſo much for a <hi>vain and empty Pomp,</hi> as a <hi>ſolemn and ſelect Fight with Wickedneſs and Vice</hi>) it can ſcarce be ſpoken or conceived, how plentiful and happy an <hi>Harveſt</hi> might be expected from this <hi>Seed-time and Tillage;</hi> what Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory againſt the Fleſh and Devil; what Trophies might be look'd for from theſe Weapons of <hi>Apoſtolical Warfare,</hi> which are not fleſhly and weak, but mighty through God, and able to deſtroy ſtrong Holds. Whereas theſe <hi>Methods of our Chriſtian Polity,</hi> having been now <hi>long deſpiſed,</hi> and either univerſally paſſing into <hi>Diſ-uſe,</hi> or framed only to an <hi>empty ſhew of Piety,</hi> and degenerating into the mere <hi>ſhadow of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal performance;</hi> or which is yet worſe, being converted to <hi>Lucre and Avarice</hi> (as the <hi>Arch-biſhop of</hi> Spalado complains) we may at this day, in vain, ſeek for the <hi>Church in the Church,</hi> the <hi>Servants of God in his Family,</hi> the <hi>Diſciples of Chriſt among Chriſtians;</hi> Nor find any thing pious and holy; but the Shadow and Name among the Candidates of Religion.)</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:48306:43"/>
                  <p> Yet once more, (<q>By this ſolemn Rite, by this, neither exceeding, nor empty Pomp of Ceremonies, the Candidate of Divine Grace is admoniſhed, <hi>meekly, ſweetly,</hi> and <hi>conſtantly to bear the Gracious Yoke of the Goſpel, taken from his Suretie's Hands upon his own Shoulders:</hi> And alſo with a <hi>Solemn Confeſſion in the open Congregation</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with the Mouth his Faith (and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution) before God, Angels and Men; and is moreover <hi>made partaker of the moſt ardent Prayers of the Biſhop; Presbyters, and whole Church: All which,</hi> whoſoever can perſuade himſelf or others, that they are like to be <hi>vain,</hi> and of <hi>no effect,</hi> he may, by the <hi>ſame Endeavor, mock at the moſt Holy Myſteries of Chriſtian Religion,</hi> as Trifles, Figments, and an unprofitable Shew or Appearance only.)</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will end this <hi>Appendix,</hi> with this plain Deſcription of <hi>Confirmation</hi> out of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes.</p>
                  <p>(It is a <hi>Sacred and Apoſtolical Rite,</hi> of moſt Ancient Uſe in the Church of Chriſt, wherein the <hi>Biſhop lays his Hand on Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Perſons, come to Years of Diſcretion,</hi> and <hi>prae-inſtructed in the Principles of their Chriſtianity:</hi> The Importance of which Performance, is, that the Parties Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, do then <hi>publickly renew and ratifie the ſolemn Vow and Promiſe made in their names
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48306:43"/>at Baptiſm,</hi> taking the ſame upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and acknowledging themſelves bound thereby; and the Biſhop <hi>confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, calls upon God, with the Congregation then preſent, for the additional Supplies of his Grace upon them; and in the Name of God, gives them his Paternal Benediction and Admonitions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>The End of the</hi> Appendix.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48306:44"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48306:44"/>
                  <p>S. BARNABAS HIS EXHORTATION To thoſe whom he Confirmed at <hi>Antioch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BEING A Practical Diſcourſe to a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Audience, to prepare them for their Biſhops <hi>CONFIRMATION.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Adhuc in ſaeculo ſumus, adhuc in acie conſtituti: danda opera eſt, ut poſt haec initia ad incrementa quoque veniatur, &amp; conſummetur in vobis, quod jam rudimentis foelicibus eſſe coepiſtis. <bibl>
                        <hi>D. Cypr. epiſt. 7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:48306:45"/>
                  <head>St. <hi>Barnabas</hi> his Exhortation to thoſe whom he Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Antioch.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Acts 11.23.</bibl>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Who, when he was come, and had ſeen the Grace of God, was glad, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them all, that with purpoſe of Heart they would cleave unto the Lord.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>BY the Diſperſion of the Chriſtian Church, upon the Perſecution that aroſe about <hi>St.</hi> Stephen <hi>the Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martyr,</hi> Divine Providence won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully brought about the Enlargement and Multiplying of it. In particular, while ſome of them were preaching the Lord <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> at <hi>Antioch,</hi> 
                     <q>The Hand of the Lord was with them, and a great number believed and turned unto the Lord, <hi>verſe</hi> 21. And when Tidings of theſe things came unto the Elders of the Church, (the <hi>Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, or Mother-Church)</hi> which was at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> (as it follows, <hi>verſe</hi> 22.)</q> they ſent forth <hi>Barnabas,</hi> one of their <hi>own Number,</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:48306:45"/>to help, aſſiſt, and <hi>confirm</hi> them in theſe good Beginnings. And how he demeaned himſelf among them, the <hi>Text</hi> acquaints us, <q>Who when he was come, and had ſeen the Grace of God, was glad, and exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all, that with purpoſe of Heart they would cleave unto the Lord.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſee then the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of the Words, and the <hi>Perſons concerned</hi> in them. The <hi>Speaker,</hi> St. <hi>Barnabas the Apoſtle,</hi> 
                     <q>A good man, and full of the Holy Ghoſt, and of Faith,</q> as we have his Character, <hi>verſe</hi> 24. And the <hi>Hearers,</hi> the <hi>Neophites, or young Converts at</hi> Antioch, unto whom he was ſent from the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm</hi> them in their Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p>And then you cannot but obſerve,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>How he was affected upon the joyful ſight of their hopeful Beginning;</hi> And,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>How he endeavored to ſtrenthen and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them unto an anſwerable perſeverance according to the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>How he was affected upon the very ſight of their hopeful Beginnings,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) <q>who when he was come, and had ſeen the Grace of God, was glad — When he was come, and had ſeen the Grace of God—)</q> The <hi>Grace of God,</hi> he means, in <hi>calling them by his Goſpel,</hi> and adding them <hi>to his Church:</hi> The Grace of God, <hi>conſpicuous in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, and turning unto the Lord;</hi> turning
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48306:46"/>
                     <hi>from Idols and Luſts to ſerve the Living and true God;</hi> This was that which affected our Apoſtle with great Joy, to behold ſo many <hi>partakers of the Word of God's Grace,</hi> and <hi>devoting themſelves upon it to the Profeſſion and Practice of Chriſtianity:</hi> For <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> than in <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> Grace is a thing <hi>inviſible,</hi> and <hi>not to be ſeen</hi> by any.</p>
                  <p>Now this is the longing and delight of <hi>all good Men,</hi> eſpecially of the <hi>Faithful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of Chriſt. Their Love to him, their Maſter, and their Love to <hi>Souls,</hi> the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of his Blood makes this <hi>ſight pleaſant and tranſporting</hi> to them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore calls the <hi>Philippians</hi> 
                     <q>His dearly belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his Joy and Crown, <hi>ch.</hi> 4.1.</q> And tells the <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> that, <q>though he was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in Body, yet he was with them in Spirit, joying and beholding their Order, and the ſtedfaſtneſs of their Faith in Chriſt,</q> 
                     <hi>ch.</hi> 2.5. And St. <hi>John</hi> writes unto the <hi>Elect Lady,</hi> That <q>He rejoyced greatly, that he found her Children walking in the Truth, 2 <hi>Ep. verſe</hi> 4.</q> And to his <hi>Hoſt Gaius,</hi> 3 <hi>Ep. verſe</hi> 3, <hi>and</hi> 4. That he <q>rejoyced greatly, when the Brethren came and teſtified of the Truth that was in him, and that he had no greater Joy, than to hear that his Children (meaning his <hi>Diſciples and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers</hi>) walked in the Truth, that is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Goſpel,</q> which is call'd both
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48306:46"/>
                     <hi>Grace and Truth</hi>— Here we may borrow the <hi>Pſalmiſt's Exclamation, Ecce quam bonum, quam jucundum!</hi> Behold, how good, and how joyful a thing it is! <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. To ſee a Society of <hi>Regular Chriſtians,</hi> combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together in the Bonds of <hi>Faith and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> and <hi>walking orderly</hi> in the <hi>Fear of God, and Love unto all men,</hi> but <hi>more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally each unto other;</hi> thus <hi>holding forth the Beauty of the word of Life in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations,</hi> and maintaining the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace. How <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing a</hi> Shew this is!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> in his <hi>Preface before his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe</hi> on St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> having recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto <hi>Novices</hi> the ſolemn Renewal of their Baptiſmal Covenant by an <hi>open and publick Profeſſion thereof</hi> (which is the <hi>thing</hi> we do at <hi>Confirmation</hi>) adds upon it (<hi>Quam verò magnificum eſſet hoc Spectaculum,</hi> &amp;c.) <q>How magnificent and glorious a Spectacle would this be, to hear the Voice of ſo many Young ones <hi>dedicating themſelves to Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> of ſo many Beginners, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging themſelves by <hi>Oath of Fidelity</hi> to him, <hi>ſwearing into his Words,</hi> to believe and obey them, <hi>renouncing the World,</hi> which lieth all in Wickedneſs, <hi>abjuring and hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in a manner at the Devil,</hi> with all his Pomps, and Pleaſures, and Works. To ſee theſe new Chriſtians, <hi>bearing the Sign
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48306:47"/>of their Emperor,</hi> the Captain of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, on their Foreheads! To behold the goodly Company of <hi>theſe Canditates,</hi> coming up from the <hi>Holy Laver;</hi> and to hear the Voice of the <hi>Multitude of Adult Chriſtians congratulating</hi> and wiſhing well to them—</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And, Oh that we had continual Matter and Occaſion for <hi>ſuch Divine Joy</hi> as this! And not rather of having our <hi>Souls grieved and vexed</hi> (with <hi>Righteous</hi> Lot's) by the graceleſs and wicked Behaviour of thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom we live, 2 St. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. Or of <hi>Lamenting</hi> (with Holy <hi>David</hi>) <q>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men keep not God's Laws, <hi>Paul</hi> 119.136.</q> becauſe of ſuch, whom St. <hi>Paul ſpeaks of to the</hi> Philippians, <hi>with Tears in his Eyes,</hi> ch. 3.18, 19. <q>The Enemies of the Croſs of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> whoſe End is Deſtruction, whoſe God is their Belly, whoſe Glory is their Shame, who mind Earthly things:</q> May we all with <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ſee more of the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> in our People, that we alſo may rejoyce and be glad in and for it!</p>
                  <p>And now, that this Joy of his might be <hi>prolonged,</hi> he proceeds, <hi>Secondly,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) to <q>
                        <hi>Exhort</hi> them all with <hi>purpoſe</hi> of Heart,</q> to cleave unto the Lord; which is the principle thing I have my Eyes at <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> upon. He <hi>encouraged them to hold on as they had begun,</hi> to <hi>abide by their own Choice;</hi>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:48306:47"/>and <q>as they had received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo to walk in him,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 2.6.7.</note> rooted and built up,</q> and eſtabliſhed in the Faith, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereingly,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perſeverantèr adhaerere Domino</hi> Eraſm. <hi>Annot. ex animo &amp; liberâ vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate) Id. propenſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de)</hi> Vatab. <hi>firmo propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito)</hi> Grot. <hi>non frididè, nec ſimulatè, ſed ſincero &amp; ardenti ſtudio)</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za.</note> to <hi>adhere to that Lord and Religion which they had em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced;</hi> and this <hi>heartily,</hi> and <hi>with a free will;</hi> with a <hi>ready mind,</hi> with a <hi>firm and ſteddy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe;</hi> not <hi>coldly or feignedly,</hi> but <hi>with Sincerity, and Fervor of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor;</hi> with <hi>Deliberation and Reſolution of Heart;</hi> that is, as the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> are wont to expreſs it, with the <hi>whole Heart,</hi> or with <hi>all the Heart and Soul;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Syriac and Arabic Interpreters here phraſe it.</hi> In a word, <hi>cordially and ſtedfaſtly to hold faſt unto Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Three points</hi> I deſign, by God's Help, to ſpeak briefly unto, in the handling of theſe words:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What is included in the <hi>Duty it ſelf</hi> here preſs'd (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to cleave unto the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="2">2, What farther in the <hi>manner of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance recommended,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) <q>with purpoſe of Heart.</q> And then,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What <hi>Arguments or Motives we may ſuppoſe the Apoſtle to have made uſe of</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force this <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or Exhortation of his to them all <q>That with purpoſe of Heart they would cleave unto the Lord.</q> Of which now in Order.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:48306:48"/>
                  <p> And Firſt, of the <hi>General Expreſſion of the Duty,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <q>to cleave unto the Lord.</q> The Greek word ſignifies to <hi>abide by,</hi> or <hi>continue with,</hi> that is, to <hi>hold on</hi> and <hi>perſevere the Diſciples and Servants of that Lord Jeſus,</hi> whom they are ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to have believed and turned unto.</p>
                  <p>When we at <hi>firſt became Chriſtians,</hi> we do, in the Sacred Language, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>come over unto Chriſt as his Proſelytes, to believe what he ſaith,</hi> and <hi>learn what he teacheth, to obſerve and obey what he commands and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns;</hi> and <hi>and ſo doing by him, as our All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Sacrifice and High-Prieſt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to the Divine Acceptance, in the aſſured Hope of Pardon, Life and Happineſs.</hi> And that we may thus come unto him, we muſt of neceſſity <hi>forſake and renounce all other contrary Lords and Maſters,</hi> whom men are wont to chuſe and adhere unto,
<note place="margin">Contit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtol.</note> in <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to him, ſuch as the <hi>Devil, the World and the Fleſh.</hi> And therefore our <hi>Baptiſmal Vow</hi> begins with an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> renun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iaveramus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> haptizati ſumus.</hi> D. Cyprian. <hi>Ep.</hi> 7. <hi>Cujus po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pis &amp; deliciis jam tunc renunciavimus, cum mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ore tranſgreſſu ad Deum venimus, id <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e Diſcip. &amp; Hab. Virg.</hi>
                     </note> or an <hi>Abrenunciation of the Enemy, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, whereby we forſake Sin with its Abetters;</hi> whereby we renounce the Devil and all his Works, the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, and all the Sinful Luſts of the Fleſh. And then follows our
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48306:48"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>Agreement with Chriſt,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>A Confeſſion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> whereby we engage our ſelves to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and profeſs all the Articles of Doctrine taught by him, and vow Obedience to all his holy Laws and Commands.</hi> Both together, make up that which St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <q>the <hi>Anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God,</hi> 1 St. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21.</q> which he there repreſents as the <hi>Saving part of Baptiſm.</hi> Some render it the <hi>Stipulation</hi> of a good <hi>Conſcience, conſiſting of a Queſtion and agreable Anſwer to it.</hi> E. gr. <hi>Q.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>H. in Loc.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <q>Doſt thou forſake the Devil?</q> 
                     <hi>A.</hi> I do. <hi>Q.</hi> 
                     <q>Doſt thou believe, <hi>&amp;c. A.</hi>
                     </q> this I ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. <hi>Q.</hi> 
                     <q>Wilt thou keep God's Holy Will and Commandments, <hi>&amp;c. A.</hi>
                     </q> I will— Others name it, <q>
                        <hi>The Addreſs of a good Conſcience unto God, enquiring of him as an Oracle to be guided by him, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him for Direction, and undertaking faithfully to obſerve and perform the ſame,</hi> asking with thoſe <hi>Goſpel Penitents,</hi> Lord, What wilt thou have me to do? Or good Maſter, <hi>What ſhall I do to inherit Eternal Life?</hi>
                     </q> With <hi>Reſolutions of Obedience,</hi> to ſet about whatever he ſhall declare— Thus in our <hi>Converſion</hi> to Chriſtianity, we <hi>diſclaim all other Lords and Maſters,</hi> as hath been ſaid, and give up our ſelves <hi>entirely unto Chriſt,</hi> to be inſtructed and ruled by
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48306:49"/>him only, to <hi>believe whatſoever he teacheth us;</hi> to <hi>ſhun and avoid whatſoever he forbids us,</hi> to <hi>endeavor and practice whatſoever he commands us,</hi> and <hi>thus to decline and eſcape that Puniſhment which he threatens,</hi> and to <hi>expect and look for that Bleſſing and Reward which he promiſeth.</hi> This is indeed to <hi>come over unto Chriſt,</hi> as his <hi>Diſciples, Servants, Subjects</hi> and <hi>Dependents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to <hi>abide by,</hi> to <hi>ſtay or continue with, or cleave unto him our Lord,</hi> is, as hath been intimated, to <hi>perſevere and hold on in this Repentance, Faith, Obedience, and good hope,</hi> patiently to <hi>bring forth Fruits meet for Repentance, anſwerable to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Life; not to fall off by Infidelity,</hi> or an <q>
                        <hi>evil Heart of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief, in departing from the Living God, Hebr.</hi> 3.12.</q> Not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe or apoſtatize by a courſe of Sin and Diſobedience; but as we have devoted our ſelves to his Faith, Fear and Service, ſo to <hi>perſiſt in an undaunted Profeſſion of that Faith, and walk before him in Holineſs and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs all our days, to live Godlily in Chriſt Jeſus, or to have a Converſation becoming the Goſpel, according to the Holy Warfare we have undertaken to fight manfully under our Bleſſed Saviour's Banner, as the good and faithful Souldiers of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> 
                     <q>Laying aſide e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Weight, and the Sin which does ſo eaſily beſet us; to run with Patience, the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48306:49"/>Race of Chriſtian Vertues preſcribed us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. Not to look or ſtart back, but hold faſt the Faith, and proceed in that good Courſe wherein we are engaged; ſhewing the ſame Diligence to the full Aſſurance of the Hope to the End; that we be not ſlothful, but followers of them, who through Faith and Patience inherit the Promiſes, <hi>ch.</hi> 6.11, 12.</q> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, '<hi>To continue in the Grace of God, Acts</hi> 13.43. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>To continue in his Goodneſs, Rom.</hi> 11.22.</q> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, '<hi>To continue in the Faith, Acts</hi> 14.22. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <q>
                        <hi>To hold faſt the Profeſſion of our Hope without wavering, Heb.</hi> 10.23.</q> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, '<hi>To ſtand faſt in the Lord, Phil.</hi> 4.3.</p>
                  <p>This is now to <hi>cleave unto the Lord,</hi> not to leave or forſake him; not to depart, or turn away from him; not to quit our Standing in his Church; not to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of him and his words; not to renounce or deny him; not to paſs over to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Side, and take the contrary part, with <hi>Renegadoes and Rebells;</hi> but to be his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and <hi>obedient Followers,</hi> perſevering in our Chriſtianity, againſt all Temptations and Diſcouragements. I will add no more about the Duty in General.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:48306:50"/>
                  <p> Secondly, That which is moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in this place, is, the <hi>manner of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it recommended to us,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, with purpoſe of Heart, that is to ſay, more at large, <hi>with a perſonal, ſincere, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate, free, firm, zealous and humble reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Give me leave to comment a little upon <hi>each of the Particulars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. It muſt be a <hi>Perſonal Engagement</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) every one for himſelf; and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Apoſtle here exhorts all to it. Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful it is to put you in mind of <hi>this,</hi> becauſe there are many, who would gladly enough have the Priviledges and Benefits of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and yet are backward themſelves to undertake the Duties of it. If they could be ſaved by what others do for them, by the Merits and good Works of others, or by ſuch a Chriſt, as ſhall cover all their Sins and Neglects, with the Mantle of his perfect Righteouſneſs, imputed to them as theirs, ſo as they may have nothing <hi>elſe to do,</hi> but boldly to rely upon him, and hope to be ſaved by him: This would pleaſe them; but they ſeem not willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern themſelves at all, in any thing of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor and Endeavor about it. Such as theſe now do miſerably cheat and delude their own Souls: For we may as well expect to be <hi>happy by Proxy</hi> in <hi>another perſon, as to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48306:50"/>perform our Duty ſo in order unto Happineſs.</hi> We muſt at laſt give an account '<hi>every one for himſelf</hi> to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.12. And then ſhall <hi>every one</hi> receive Sentence from him, according to what he hath done in the Fleſh, whether good or evil; and ſo <hi>every one</hi> ſhall then have Praiſe from him, or bear his own Burden, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>&amp;e.</hi> We muſt every one appear perſonally before the Great Tribunal of our Eternal Judge, and cannot anſwer for one another there. And in the mean while, we are obliged to <q>work out our own Salvation by a <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Faith,</hi> and <hi>Obedience of our own, Phil.</hi> 2.12.</q> 
                     <q>God now commandeth all men every where to repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30.</q> And <q>the Juſt, ſaith the Prophet, ſhall live by his Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4.</q> Every man muſt believe and confeſs for himſelf: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that our <hi>Creed</hi> runs in the Firſt Perſon ſingular, <hi>Credo, I believe.</hi> Every man muſt be fully <hi>perſuaded in his own mind,</hi> Rom. 14.5. and have a <hi>Stedfaſtneſs of his own,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> intimates, 2 <hi>Ep. ch.</hi> 3.7. <q>Beware, leſt ye alſo, being led away with the Error of the Wicked, fall from your own Stedfaſtneſs.</q> Chriſt muſt be <hi>Spiritually formed in every one of us,</hi> that is, <hi>his Image,</hi> which is ſometimes called the <hi>New man,</hi> muſt be drawn upon us. <q>My little Children, ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> of whom I
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48306:51"/>travel in Birth again, until Chriſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med within you.</q> 
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. And it is This Chriſt in us, which is <hi>Hope of Glory.</hi> We muſt every one be <hi>thus born again,</hi> and <hi>become new Creatures.</hi> The Bleſſed Jeſus himſelf, <hi>once and again avers</hi> it to <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> 
                     <q>Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man be born again (or <hi>from above,</hi> as the <hi>Margin</hi> reads it) he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God.</q> And then he <hi>repeats</hi> it, <q>Verily, verily, I ſay unto thee, except a man be born of Water, and of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God, St. <hi>John</hi> 3.3.5.</q> The Indefinite Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation here reacheth every one, <q>
                        <hi>Except a man</hi>—</q> What he ſaith to <hi>one</hi> in this caſe, is ſaid to <hi>all;</hi> and what is ſpoken ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally unto <hi>all,</hi> extendeth unto every <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We cannot be Chriſtians without our <hi>own Conſent:</hi> For how otherwiſe can we be <hi>eſpouſed to Chriſt?</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet ſpeaks emphatically of <hi>Goſpel-Converts, ch.</hi> 44.4, 5. <q>One ſhall ſay, I am the Lord's, and another ſhall call himſelf by the Name of <hi>Jacob;</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall ſubſcribe with his Hands unto the Lord, and Sir-name himſelf by the name of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>True it is, while we were <hi>Infants,</hi> we were brought to Chriſt in the <hi>Arms</hi> of thoſe,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48306:51"/>who then undertok for us; and ſuch who cannot come otherwiſe, are welcom'd by him, when ſo brought by their Friends, and devoted to him. <q>Suffer the little Children <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> to come unto me, and forbid them not; for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God. And he took them in his Arms, put his Hands upon them, and bleſſed them.</q> St. <hi>Mark</hi> 10. which words are excellently commented upon in our <hi>Office of Publick Baptiſm.</hi> We allow therefore of the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble interpoſure of <hi>others,</hi> to tranſact in the Name of Infants for their Good and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, who are not in capacity, to mind or do any thing themſelves (<hi>Accommodat illis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia aliorum pedes, ut veniant, aliorum cor,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Serm.</hi> 10. <hi>de verb. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtol.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ut credant, aliorum linguam, ut confiteantur,</hi> as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath it) <q>The Church lends them the <hi>Feet of others to come,</hi> and the <hi>Heart of others to believe,</hi> and the <hi>Tongue of others to confeſs</hi>— But then we do <hi>as plainly declare,</hi> that <hi>ſo ſoon as they are able,</hi> they muſt <hi>themſelves own and acknowledge, ſtand to,</hi> and <hi>make good the Sacred Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
                     </q> made by others for them and in their Names: that <hi>Repentance,</hi> whereby they are to forſake Sin; and that <hi>Faith,</hi> whereby they are ſtedfaſtly to believe the Promiſes of God, ſo as to become <hi>obedient to his Commands</hi> upon it: All this, which was vowed by their Sureties, in their Names,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48306:52"/>
                     <hi>themſelves, when they are come to Age, are bound to perform.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this is that, which every one among us, in his <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> is train'd up <hi>to profeſs,</hi> that he doth <hi>verily believe himſelf ſo bound,</hi> and that, <hi>by God's Help, he will do accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly:</hi> And ſo we <hi>ſolemnly affirm, with our own Mouths, at our Confirmation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We are upon <hi>no other Terms admitted</hi> to a State of Salvation in our Baptiſm, than this indiſpenſable Obligation, ſo ſoon as we grow up, our ſelves to ratifie and make good, what was then undertaken and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed for us: And if there be any, who are afterwards unwilling to conſent unto thoſe Terms, or refuſe to <hi>confirm</hi> the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Vow, made in their Names, they are to know and conſider, that they <hi>bar them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the ſaving Benefit of their Baptiſm,</hi> and do, in effect, proclaim, that <hi>were it now to be done, they would not be made Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians upon theſe Conditions:</hi> and yet they <hi>cannot</hi> be admitted upon <hi>any other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This I have thought convenient to warn and admoniſh you of in the <hi>Firſt Place,</hi> that every one muſt engage for <hi>himſelf,</hi> ſo as to make <hi>Religion his own,</hi> ſo as to have a Repentance, and Faith, and Obedience, and Stedfaſtneſs of his own. The <hi>Purpoſe of the Heart is a Perſonal Act,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:48306:52"/> 2. It muſt be <hi>ſincere and and honeſt.</hi> This I will give you a ſhort Explication of in <hi>three Particulars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. It muſt not be in <hi>Shew and Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> or <hi>Formality</hi> only, but <hi>Cordial,</hi> and <hi>with the Heart.</hi> (That is one Derivation of the word Sincere, from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) God is not taken with the external Complements of Devotion, when the Heart is not with him: but complains of their <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> who <q>draw near unto him with their Mouths, and honor him with their Lips, while their Hearts are far removed from him; and of ſuch he teſtifies, that in vain they worſhip him, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 29.13. St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8, 9.</q> That of St. <hi>John</hi> is to be extended to our <hi>Love unto God,</hi> as well as to <hi>to our Neighbor,</hi> 
                     <q>Let us not love in word, neither in Tongue only,</q> but in Deed and in Truth, 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 3.18.</p>
                  <p>The Heart muſt be upright and ſimple (that is another Derivation, <hi>ſine cerâ</hi>) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>mixture of contrary Deſigns and Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> as when <hi>Herod</hi> pretended a deſire to <hi>worſhip</hi> Chriſt, but meant to have <hi>kill'd</hi> him: or as <hi>Jezebel</hi> proclaimed a Faſt in ſhew of Juſtice; but intended the <hi>Murther</hi> of Innocent <hi>Naboth;</hi> or as when the <hi>Phariſees</hi> appeared devout in their Long Prayers and Faſtings, and <hi>charitable</hi> in their Alms-giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but their end was only to <hi>get a Name
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48306:53"/>to themſelves,</hi> have the Praiſe and Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Beholders, and cheat with the greater Color, <hi>devouring Widdows Houſes;</hi> or as when <hi>Judas</hi> gave our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our a <hi>Kiſs;</hi> but with a wicked porpoſe to <hi>betray</hi> him— We muſt be hearty and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere in our Religion, not in <hi>ſhew and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence only</hi> (as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks of ſome, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 2.20.42.20. and the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.34, 36, 37. <q>Diſſembling in their Hearts, and lying with their Tongues) but in Truth and Reality;</q> not to carry on ſiniſter and unworthy Deſigns, under that <hi>Mask and Vizard,</hi> but with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of Soul, and Uprightneſs of Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And then,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This ſincere Honeſty will diſcover it ſelf by the <hi>Equality and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality of our Faith and Obedience;</hi> not <hi>picking and chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> what points we like beſt to approve of, or what Commandments we can reconcile to the Intereſt of our Luſts and Humors; but embracing <hi>all God's Declarations</hi> with the ſame readineſs of <hi>Faith,</hi> becauſe <hi>He hath ſpoken them,</hi> and all his <hi>Commands,</hi> with the ſame Obſervance, becauſe <hi>he enjoyns them.</hi> This is that which the Scripture calls <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;</hi> as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> well notes on <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hom.</hi> 23. <hi>in</hi> Gen.</note> 6. <hi>Noah was a juſt man, and perfect,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>)
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48306:53"/>
                     <q>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed (ſaith <hi>Holy David</hi>) when I have Reſpect unto all thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Pſalm,</hi> 119.6. I will have reſpect unto thy Statutes continually, <hi>verſe</hi> 117. I eſteem all thy Precepts concerning all things to be right; and I hate every falſe way, <hi>ver.</hi> 128.</q> And thus it is ſaid of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> 
                     <q>They are both right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous before God, walking in all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Ordinances of the Lord, blameleſs, St. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6.</q> And ſo it muſt needs be: For if that be the <hi>reaſon of our Faith, becauſe God declares the matter unto us,</hi> we muſt of neceſſity, on the <hi>ſame</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, believe every <hi>thing ſo declared:</hi> And if that be the <hi>Reaſon of our Obedience, becauſe God commands the thing,</hi> we muſt upon the ſame account obey whatſoever is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: And for us to renounce any one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, or live in the open Breach and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of any known Command, is, by way of juſt Interpretation, to renounce and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey them all, while we oppoſe that <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and <hi>Formal Reaſon of Faith and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> which runs through them all alike. And ſo St. <hi>James</hi> plainly tells us, <hi>ch.</hi> 2.10, 11. <q>Whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point <hi>(wilfully, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Choice offend in one point)</hi> is guilty of all.</q>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:48306:54"/>For <q>he that ſaid (or <hi>that Law which ſaid</hi>) Do not commit Adultery, ſaid alſo, Do not kill. Now, if thou commit no Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, yet if thou kill, thou art become a Tranſgreſſor of the Law.—</q> If we are only for <hi>This and that Article of Faith,</hi> or for <hi>this and that Command,</hi> it is manifeſt, that we <hi>pleaſe our ſelves only,</hi> and <hi>do our own Will;</hi> but if we therefore believe any one point, becauſe <hi>God hath declared</hi> it; or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any one Duty, becauſe <hi>God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned it:</hi> The very ſame Reſpect and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will inforce upon us, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſality</hi> in our Faith and Obedience: And we cannot be ſincere without this. <q>We truſt (ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>) that we have a good Conſcience in all things willing to live honeſtly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.18.</q> We have no good Conſcience at all, if we are not in all things willing to live honeſtly. We are no <hi>upright</hi> Chriſtians, if we are not thus truly <hi>Catholick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our purpoſe of Heart then muſt be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,
<note place="margin"> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, St. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> as hath been ſaid, in oppoſition unto <hi>Simulation and Hypocriſie, Complement and Formality, Defect and Partiality</hi> in our Faith and Obedience; the purpoſe of a <hi>good and honeſt Heart,</hi> as 'tis call'd in the <hi>Parable,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> St. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.15.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It muſt be <hi>underſtanding</hi> and <hi>deliberate</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:48306:54"/>in oppoſition to <hi>ignorance and raſhneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are many perſons, (who yet would be thought to renounce <hi>Popery</hi>) for an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Faith in the General,</hi> and a <hi>blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in the Lump,</hi> without ſtudying or conſidering the <hi>particular Doctrines</hi> to be believed, or the <hi>particular Laws</hi> to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed. There are many well enough re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and brought to this, to diſown and renounce Sin in the <hi>General,</hi> while God knows, there is hardly any <hi>particular Sin,</hi> which they are not ready to cloſe with up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Firſt Temptation to it. And ſo in like manner, there are many that will, <hi>Hand over Head,</hi> as we ſay, <hi>engage to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (as men cuſtomarily embrace the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of their <hi>Country</hi> or <hi>Education</hi>) never conſidering what it may coſt them to make good this Engagement in its particulars: And for want of this it is, that afterwards they <hi>fall away.</hi> We on the other ſide, are call'd upon <q>not to be unwiſe, but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what the Will of our Lord is,</q> 
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.17. And our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the <hi>Multitude that flock'd after him, to bethink themſelves, how much was expected of thoſe who would be altogether Chriſtians, and owned by him among his genuine Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> 
                     <q>There went out Multitudes with him, ſaith the <hi>Text,</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he turned, and ſaid unto them, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48306:55"/>man come to me, and hate not his Father, and Mother, and Wife, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and Brethren, and Siſters; yea, and his own Life alſo;</q> (if he hate not all theſe <hi>in compariſon of me;</hi> or if he <hi>love not me above all theſe,</hi> ſo as upon occaſion, for my ſake to leave and quit all theſe, St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37. 'he cannot be my Diſciple. Thus much he earneſtly recommends to their ſerious Conſideration at the very <hi>firſt ſetting out (ne magis feriant improviſa tela;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Grot. in loc.</note> 
                     <hi>atque itâ, quod quis aggreſſus eſt temerè, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ſuo malo deſerat, factus</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) that they might not be <hi>ſurprized</hi> with Difficulties, never before dream'd of by them, and ſo baſely <hi>revolt</hi> from their profeſſion after ſome <hi>plauſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ble,</hi> but <hi>raſh</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings. To this purpoſe he gives them a <hi>double Similitude</hi> from what was <hi>uſual in other matters</hi> among thoſe of ordinary Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Wiſdom in the World, <hi>ver.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <q>For which of you, intending to build a Tower, ſitteth not down firſt, and and counteth the Coſt, whether he have ſufficient to finiſh it? Leſt happily, after that he hath laid the Foundation, and is not able to finiſh it all that behold it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to mock him, ſaying, This man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to build, and was not able to finiſh; or what King, going to make War againſt another King, ſitteth not down firſt and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48306:55"/>conſulteth, whether he be able with ten thouſand, to meet him that cometh againſt him with twenty thouſand; or elſe, while the other is yet a great way off, he ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an Embaſſage, and deſireth Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Peace?</q> — Thus (ſaith he) in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſhould you <hi>ponder well before-hand,</hi> what the <hi>buſineſs</hi> is which you undertake when you become Chriſtians, what <hi>Coſts</hi> and <hi>Charges,</hi> what <hi>Pains</hi> and <hi>Labors</hi> you thereby oblige your ſelves unto; that you may enter on that Profeſſion <hi>underſtanding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and with a <hi>Proſpect of the worſt</hi> that may afterwards befall you in or for it; that ſo you may go through with <hi>your Building,</hi> and <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh your Warfare.</hi> In the <hi>cloſe of all,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he adds, that he might bring the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to its due <hi>Iſſue, verſe</hi> 33. <q>So likewiſe, whoſoever he be of you, that forſaketh not all that he hath, (that is, who <hi>ſets not forth with this Diſpoſition of Soul,</hi> to quit all rather than my Faith and Service) he cannot be my Diſciple.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Reſolves you ſee in Religion, muſt not be blind and raſh, but <hi>rational and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate,</hi> upon a prae-conſideration, both of the <hi>particulars of our Chriſtianity</hi> (what it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth us to believe, profeſs and do] and of the <hi>ſeveral Hazards</hi> which it may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us to. <q>I have choſen the way of truth, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> thy Judgments have I
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:48306:56"/>laid before me, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.30.</q> That is the right method certainly to a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>durable Choice,</hi> firſt, to lay God's Judgments as diſtinctly as may be before our View (as the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>panis propoſitionis,</hi> or <hi>Shew-bread placed on the Table under the Law</hi>) with the <hi>Conſequences</hi> attending the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of them, that we may ſay, whatever enſues or falls out, <hi>Omnia praecepi atque ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo mecum ante peregi, All this I was well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough aware of, when I firſt undertook my Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe that <hi>hear the Goſpel preached, and underſtand it not,</hi> are reſembled by our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour to the <hi>High-way ground,</hi> where the <hi>Seed is wholly loſt;</hi> and thoſe who do not conſider <hi>and deliberate upon it</hi> within themſelves to the <hi>Stony Ground,</hi> where the Seed takes not any <hi>deep and kindly Rooting,</hi> or hath not <hi>much Earth (or Mould)</hi> to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it; and therefore, howſoever, for the <hi>preſent,</hi> it may be <hi>received with Joy,</hi> yet it dureth for a <hi>while only:</hi> For <q>when Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Perſecution ariſeth becauſe of the Word, by and by (ſaith he) theſe are offended, <hi>S. Matth.</hi> 13.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. This Conſideration and Deliberation, I have been ſpeaking of, muſt not reſt there, but conclude in a <hi>free, firm, and zealous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution;</hi> where we have <hi>four points</hi> more to meditate a while upon.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:48306:56"/> 1. It muſt come up to a Reſolution, that is, the <hi>actual Determination of the Mind and Choice,</hi> according to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> 
                     <q>I have <hi>applyed, or inclined my Heart</hi> to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil thy Statutes always, even to the End, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.112.</q> And again, <hi>elſewhere,</hi> 
                     <q>My Heart is fixed,</q> O God, my heart is fixed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.8. — <q>Who is this that <hi>engaged his Heart to approach</hi> unto me,</q> ſaith the Lord? <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.21. We muſt not always be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and deliberating; but bring the Matter to ſome <hi>Period and Iſſue</hi> within our ſelves; and that, not only as to ſome <hi>faint Wiſhes and Velleities,</hi> but <hi>Purpoſes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions</hi> of cleaving unto God: Such as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid often expreſſeth,</hi> 
                     <q>I ſaid, I will take heed to my ways, I will keep my Mouth as with a Bridle, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1.</q> 
                     <q>I have ſaid, that I will keep thy Words, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.57. I have purpoſed, that my Mouth ſhall not tranſgreſs, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <q>How long halt ye between two Opinions, ſaith the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet?</hi>
                     </q> If God be God, follow him, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. that is, <hi>reſolve and conclude upon it,</hi> as you have all reaſon to do, to ſerve him only.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This Reſolution muſt be free <hi>and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary,</hi> not as upon <hi>Conſtraint,</hi> or of <hi>Nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſity,</hi> or a <hi>forced Put;</hi> not as a <hi>Burthen</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; but, as hath been ſaid, a matter of <hi>Choice;</hi> and that upon <hi>matureſt Thoughts</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, <hi>the cheerful Offering of a willing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48306:57"/>mind.</hi> Such is that Service which is moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God: He loves a <hi>chearful Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and a <hi>chearful Servant,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11, 12.— 9, 6, 7. He delights in none but <hi>Volunteers,</hi> a <hi>willing People, Pſ.</hi> 110.3. Such as eſteem not his Commands <hi>grievous,</hi> 1 <hi>St. John</hi> 5.3. Such as do not only take <hi>Sanctuary in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to avoid the Hand of the Avenger,</hi> or embrace Piety and Vertue, <hi>meerly to eſcape Wrath and Miſery, Hell and Damnation;</hi> but from an <hi>Inward Satisfaction and Complacence in the Truth, and Goodneſs, and Excellency</hi> of them. Thus we found it in the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> 
                     <q>I have choſen the way of Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> And thus <hi>Joſhua</hi> deals with the <hi>Iſraelites, ch.</hi> 24.14, 15. <q>Fear the Lord (ſaith he) and ſerve him in Sincerity and Truth (cleave <hi>unto him,</hi> and that out of Love, as he had ſaid before) and put away the Gods which your Fathers ſerved (that is, <hi>all manner of Idols</hi>) and if it ſeem evil unto you to ſerve the Lord (upon theſe Terms) chuſe you this day whom you will ſerve—</q>But, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you chuſe, <hi>I for my part have choſen and reſolved already.</hi> 
                     <q>As for me and my Houſe we will ſerve the Lord.</q> Whereupon the <hi>People,</hi> provoked unto <hi>Emulation,</hi> anſwer alſo for themſelves, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <q>God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that we ſhould forſake the Lord our God,</q> he it is that bought us and our Fathers <q>out of the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> from the Houſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:48306:57"/>of Bondage, and which did thoſe Great Signs in our Sight, and preſerved us in all the way wherein we went, and went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the People, through whom we paſſed; and the Lord drove out before us all the People, even the <hi>Amorites</hi> which dwell in the Land: Therefore will we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſerve the Lord,</q> for he is our God, — <hi>q. d.</hi> He is the God of our <hi>Lives,</hi> and of <hi>all our Mercies;</hi> who hath wrought <hi>all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> we have beheld; rescued us out of <hi>cruel Servitude;</hi> and kept us in all the way <hi>of our Travails;</hi> delivered us from <hi>moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Enemies.</hi> Thus hath he many ways, from <hi>time to time,</hi> obliged us to himſelf; and therefore, as in all <hi>Gratitude</hi> we are bound, we are reſolv'd alſo to ſerve him— Well, but <hi>Joſhua</hi> is yet concern'd, leſt they ſhould not be ſo <hi>adviſed and thoughtful</hi> in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution as it became them in ſuch a Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Importance to be; and therefore wills them <hi>again to deliberate</hi> with themſelves about it, <hi>what they muſt engage on,</hi> if they would in good earneſt ſerve him; how they muſt renounce <hi>all other Maſters,</hi> and <hi>aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all their Sins and Luſts;</hi> or otherwiſe he would accept of no Service from them. So it follows, <hi>verſe</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'And <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſaid unto the People, ye cannot ſerve the <q>Lord, for he is an Holy God, he is a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God; he will not forgive your Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48306:58"/>nor your Sins. If ye forſake the Lord, and ſerve ſtrange Gods, then he will turn, and do you hurt, and conſume you, after he hath done you good—</q> That is, you cannot ſerve the Lord to any <hi>purpoſe,</hi> unleſs you amend your Lives and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now upon this the People again declare their Intentions: <q>Nay, but we will ſerve the Lord.</q> And <hi>Joſhua once and again admoniſhes them</hi> ſtill to the ſame effect, and they as often <hi>conſent to his propoſal,</hi> 
                     <q>Ye are witneſſes againſt your ſelves, <hi>ſaith he at laſt,</hi> that ye have choſen you the Lord to ſerve him. And they ſaid <hi>Amen</hi> to it. We are Witneſſes— Now therefore, ſaith he, put away the ſtrange Gods which are among you, and incline your Heart unto the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     </q> that is, make good <hi>your own Choice in cleaving unto him.</hi> And the People ſaid unto <hi>Joſhua,</hi> 
                     <q>The Lord our God will we ſerve, and his Voice will we obey.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. This purpoſe of Heart muſt be <hi>ſixed, firm and ſtable;</hi> for that indeed is properly Reſolution, <hi>obſtinatio quaedam animi, a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Obſtinacy of Mind</hi> (if I may ſo ſpeak) ſo as no longer to be wavering and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>carried to and fro with every Wind;</hi> not apt to <hi>receive contrary Impreſſions,</hi> or be <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and turned aſide, either by Promiſes or Menaces</hi> from what is reſolved on. The
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48306:58"/>
                     <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> utters it in theſe <hi>words</hi> 
                     <q>I have <hi>ſworn,</hi> and am <hi>ſtedfaſtly purpoſed</hi> to keep thy Righteous Judgments, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</q> And <hi>elſewhere,</hi> in a particular Caſe, <q>Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>David,</hi>— how he ſware unto the Lord, and vowed unto the Mighty God of <hi>Jacob, Pſal.</hi> 132. that is, <hi>bound his Soul with the ſtricteſt Bond hereunto</hi> — The like <hi>Inflexibility</hi> we may obſerve,</q> upon Tryal,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2.</note> in the <hi>Three Famous Confeſſors,</hi> and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Flaming <hi>Furnace,</hi> threatning of them; they declare <hi>peremptorily,</hi> that <hi>whatever come of it,</hi> they will not ſerve any Idol, or fall down to the Golden Image, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. <q>Our God, <hi>ſay they,</hi> is able to deliver us from the burning Fiery Furnace, and he will deliver us out of thy Hand, O King— but if not <hi>(be that as it will)</hi> be it known unto thee, O King, that we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip thy Golden Image,</q> which thou haſt ſet up — Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remarkable Story we have of St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 21, 12, 13, 14. Where neither the greateſt of <hi>Dangers,</hi> nor yet <hi>the Tears and Solicitations of his Friends</hi> are able to move or diſſuade him from his Holy purpoſe. <q>What mean ye to weep, and to break mine Heart, ſaith he? For I am ready not to be bound only, but alſo to die at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                     </q> for the Name of the Lord Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> A Reſolution, when it comes to this <hi>degree
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48306:59"/>of Firmitude,</hi> when it ariſeth to the height of a <hi>Sacred Oath and Vow,</hi> an <hi>Obligation of our ſelves to God by ſolemn Promiſe and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a ſure and ſealed Covenant</hi> (as it is <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem.</hi> 9.38,) is of <hi>mighty Power and Effect</hi> in Religion. For ſo we find it in all other matters, when men are <hi>reſolutely wicked,</hi> perverſe and obſtinate in any courſe, as the <hi>Horſe ruſhing into the Battel,</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>Their Hearts fully ſet in them to do evil, Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11.</q> Say or do what you will, there is no <hi>ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or turning of them.</hi> The ſame <hi>Fixation</hi> we ſhould labor after in our <hi>Pious Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> until we bring our ſelves unto an <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt unalterable Reſolution and Temper (Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec bona mens ſit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ep. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>quod bona voluntas eſt; &amp; habitus fiat, quod eſt impetus,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> hath it.)</p>
                  <p>And if it be thus in any good meaſure with us, there is no queſtion but that,</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We ſhall be zealous and affectionate alſo in theſe our deliberate, free, and firm Reſolutions: For our <hi>whole Heart</hi> will be engaged in them; and <hi>all Indifferency, Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Lukewarmneſs, ariſeth from nothing but the Diviſion of the Heart, among divers and contrary Objects, (pluribus intentus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor eſt ad ſingula</hi>—) Thus we are to be <q>fervent in Spirit ſerving the Lord, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.</q> And this Zeal will ſhew it ſelf, eſpecially<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in <hi>breaking through all manner of Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48306:59"/>Oppoſitions, Letts and Hindrances,</hi> in the way of our Bounden Duty. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will be able to ſtand againſt, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Powerful Flames of it. But if we are <hi>neither Cold nor Hot</hi> in our Religion, God, as he threateneth <hi>the Laodicean Church,</hi> will <hi>ſpew us out of his Mouth.</hi> 
                     <q>Be zealous therefore (ſaith he) and repent, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.</q> 
                     <hi>(Qui ſuſceptus es quaſi intra Os Dei per fidei agnitionem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Salvian. de Gub. l.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>projicieris per Teporem)</hi> as the <hi>Devout Father gloſſeth vpon it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. And Laſtly, to prevent Miſcarriage in all this, it will be requiſite that we add <hi>Humility of Soul</hi> unto the reſt; whereby I mean <hi>a deep Sence of our own Weakneſs and Infirmity, as of our ſelves, and the neceſſity we ſtand in continually of Divine Aid and Help,</hi> which will prompt us to a <hi>conſtant dependence upon God,</hi> and <hi>calling on him for his Grace, and Watchfulneſs over our ſelves in the time of Temptation,</hi> leſt we be worſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and overcome, leſt we ſhould ſtart aſide <hi>like a broken Bow,</hi> and fail of performing our Holy Promiſes unto God. We muſt beware of <hi>leaning to our own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and preſuming <hi>upon our own Strength.</hi> 
                     <q>Let him that thinketh that he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12.</q> God is to be duly acknowledged by us in <hi>all our ways;</hi> and our Hearts and Souls are to be at all times lift up towards him for his
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48306:60"/>Succor and Bleſſing, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Recruits</hi> in the time of need, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13. —</p>
                  <p>Who was more confident and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous of himſelf than St. <hi>Peter?</hi> 
                     <q>Though all men ſhall be offended becauſe of thee, yet will I never be offended (ſaith he) St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.</q> Yea, and after that our Bleſſed Saviour had given him a <hi>Check,</hi> and foretold his Fall more particularly, <q>Verily I ſay unto thee, that this Night, before the Cock crow,</q> thou ſhalt deny me thrice. Nevertheleſs, he <hi>repeats</hi> it with a <hi>freſh degree of Earneſtneſs and Vehemency.</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) 'Though I ſhould die with thee,
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.31.</note> yet will I not deny thee: And ſo it ſeems, <hi>after his Example promiſed all the Diſciples</hi>— But we know the <hi>ſad Conſequence,</hi> how, <q>When the <hi>Shepherd was ſmitten,</hi> the <hi>Sheep were all ſcatered,</hi> they <hi>all forſook him:</hi>
                     </q> And this <hi>over-confident Apoſtle,</hi> even with <hi>a Curſe and Oath,</hi> renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his Maſter. A fair warning to <hi>us all,</hi> to lay to Heart and put in practice the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Advice which our Bleſſed Saviour a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before gave them.</hi> 
                     <q>Watch and pray that ye enter not into Temptation;</q> and to <hi>pray daily,</hi> as he hath taught us, <q>Lead us not into Temptation, but deliver us from Evil.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:48306:60"/>
                  <p> And thus now we have the <hi>particulars</hi> comprized in the Text, what St. <hi>Barnabas</hi> exhorted them all unto, both for the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Duty,</hi> and for <hi>the manner of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance</hi> 'with purpoſe of Heart to cleave unto the Lord, that is, as you have heard, with a <hi>perſonal, ſincere, deliberate, free, firm, zealous, and yet humble Reſolution of Soul, to hold faſt, and perſevere in their Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It remains only in the <hi>Third place,</hi> that I point you to ſome of thoſe <hi>General Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Arguments,</hi> which we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, this <hi>Good Man,</hi> this <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (as his name is interpreted, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.36.) made uſe of in <hi>preſſing of his Exhortation upon them all;</hi> which I hope you will every one apply to your ſelves, whilſt I ſhall little more than name the particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Then we may ſuppoſe, that he ſet before them the <hi>abſolute neceſſity</hi> of this Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian perſeverance from the very Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <hi>Vow of their firſt Admiſſion and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance</hi> upon that <hi>Holy Profeſſion</hi>—. And that he ſuggeſted unto them, that <hi>all their good Beginnings would be loſt and in vain,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they were thus followed on, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by them— That if they <hi>drew back,</hi> it would be <hi>unto Perdition;</hi> and no Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Souls was to be hoped for, unleſs they believed <hi>unto the end;</hi> no <hi>Crown,</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:48306:61"/>but to him that <hi>overcometh</hi> — Nay, if they Apoſtatized and Revolted, the <hi>later End would be worſe with them than the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi> and <hi>their Condemnation the more ſad and heavy;</hi> ſo that it had been <hi>better for them never to have known and owned the way of Truth and Righteouſneſs,</hi> than after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards unworthily to relinquiſh and forſake it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We may ſuppoſe, he ſet before them the <hi>well grounded Divinity,</hi> and <hi>ſurpaſſing Excellency of that Religion, which they had now embraced, far above all others</hi>— to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with the moſt <hi>reaſonable Service</hi> therein required and call'd for, which is <hi>moſt ſuitable to, and perfective of our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature,</hi> conſidered both in <hi>every In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual,</hi> and as it is <hi>embodied in the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Societies of Men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. We may ſuppoſe, he repreſented to them the <hi>Goodneſs, and obligingneſs of that Lord and Maſter</hi> to whom they had devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves— <hi>How well he had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of them</hi>— what tranſcendent and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Love</hi> he had ſhewed to them, in <hi>giving himſelf to and for them,</hi> and redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them with his moſt <hi>precious Blood</hi>— And how <hi>ready he was ſtill at all times to ſtand by them for their Help and Aſſiſtance</hi> in whatſoever he ſhould call them to.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:48306:61"/> 4. It is not unlikely, but he might bring into their View the great <hi>Cloud of Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes encompaſſing of them round about:</hi> The many <hi>good Examples and Preſidents,</hi> both under the <hi>Old and New Teſtament,</hi> whom they were herein to follow— And then</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> We may be ſure he put them in mind of the <hi>exceeding and incomparable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of Reward,</hi> which would be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly theirs, if by patient Continuance in well-doing they look'd and waited for it— A Reward of <hi>Eternal Life and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and Glory,</hi> wherewith neither the <hi>good,</hi> nor the <hi>evil</hi> things of this World, which are but for a moment, are worthy to be weighed— <hi>Concluding</hi> to a like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as we find St. <hi>Paul,</hi> his <hi>Brother and Companion</hi> in that Work, doth to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>ult.</hi> And <hi>I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude better than</hi> ſo. <q>Therefore, my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Brethren, be ye ſtedfaſt, unmoveable, always abounding in the Work of the Lord; foraſmuch as you know that your Labor is not in vain in the Lord.</q>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Lord of all Power and Might, who art the Author and Giver of all good things, graft in our Hearts the Love of thy Name; Increaſe in us true Religion, nouriſh us with all Goodneſs; and of thy great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy keep us in the ſame, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:48306:62"/>
                     <p> Lord, we beſeech thee, grant thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Grace to withſtand the Temptations of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil; and with pure Hearts and Minds, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee, the only God, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O God, Foraſmuch as without thee we are notable to pleaſe thee, mercifully grant, that thy Holy Spirit may in all things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and rule our Hearts, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O God, who knoweſt us to be ſet in the midſt of ſo many and great Dangers, that by reaſon of the Frailty of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we cannot always ſtand upright; grant to us ſuch Strength and Protection, as may ſupport us in all Dangers, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry us through all Temptations, through Jeſus Chriſt, our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O God, who haſt prepared for them that love thee, ſuch good things as paſs man's Underſtanding; pour into our Hearts ſuch Love towards thee, that we, loving thee above all things, may obtain thy Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which exceed all that we can deſire, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:48306:62"/>
                  <head>A TABLE OF THE <hi>CHIEF CONTENTS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>OF the Scope and Sence of</hi> Hebr. 6.2. page. 1.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Our Church-Catechiſm moſt agreeable to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical</hi> p. 5.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the Names whereby</hi> Confirmation <hi>is known and call'd,</hi> viz.
<list>
                           <item>Impoſition, <hi>or laying on of Hands</hi> 7.</item>
                           <item>Perfection 8.</item>
                           <item>Chriſm, <hi>or</hi> Unction 9.</item>
                           <item>Conſigning, <hi>or</hi> Sealing 10.</item>
                           <item>Confirmation 11.</item>
                           <item>Obligation 12.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:48306:63"/>
                     <item>2 Tim. 2.19. <hi>Well accommodated by Dr.</hi> Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond <hi>to this matter</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Moſt of the precedent Names found in</hi> 2 Cor. 1.21, 22. 14.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Other Scripture Paterns and Grounds for it</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Figur'd out, and pointed to us in the viſible Deſcent of the Holy Spirit.</hi> 1. <hi>On our Bleſſed Saviour in the Form of a Dove, St.</hi> Matthew 3. ib.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>On the Apoſtles afterwards at</hi> Pentecoſt Acts 2. ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Recommended by Chriſt himſelf, St.</hi> John 3.5. <hi>as Biſhop</hi> Taylor <hi>with St.</hi> Cyprian <hi>expounded that Text</hi> 15.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubtedly practiced by the Apoſtles, St.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>and</hi> John <hi>Confirming the</hi> Samaritans, <hi>Baptized by</hi> Philip <hi>the Deacon,</hi> Acts 8. <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>the</hi> Epheſians, Acts 19. 16.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Theſe Inſtances ſo underſtood and appeal'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by St.</hi> Cyprian 17.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>St.</hi> Auguſtin 19.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>St.</hi> Hierom ibid.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>As will as by the Church of</hi> England 20.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Some other Scripture Inſtances glanced at,</hi> Acts 11.14, 15. <hi>Chapters</hi> 21.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>This Apoſtolical Practice both a Light unto, and farther Illuſtrated, by</hi> Hebr. 6.2. <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded accordingly by the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> ib.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:48306:63"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Additional Authority of the Council of</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberis <hi>and</hi> Tertullian 22.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſame allowed by the Generallity of Modern Expoſitors alſo</hi> ibid.
<list>
                           <item>Calviniſts, <hi>as</hi> Calvin 23</item>
                           <item>Beza 25.</item>
                           <item>Piſcator 26.</item>
                           <item>Doctores Lugdun. 27.</item>
                           <item>Lutherans, Chemnitius 28.</item>
                           <item>Waldenſes-<hi>Confeſs &amp; Apolog.</hi> 30.</item>
                           <item>Bohemian <hi>Brethren,</hi> Comenius. <hi>Ratio Diſciplin. &amp;c.</hi> 32</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>With ſome of Name among our ſelves,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mr.</hi> Hanmer, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Baxter 34.</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Dr.</hi> William Gouge ib.</item>
                           <item>Aſſembl. <hi>Annotations</hi> 35.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the Ceremony of Impoſition of Hands</hi> 37.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Calvin<hi>'s Idle Queſtion about it anſwered from his more calm and conſidering ſelf</hi> 39.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Bleſſing of Miniſters under the Goſpel, no leſs Authoritative and Prolifique than under the Law</hi> 41</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the peculiar Miniſter of</hi> Confirmation, <hi>the</hi> Biſhop, <hi>whence it is called</hi> Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping 42.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>So in the firſt Patterns, and ſo confeſſedly, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of the Ancient Church</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Bucer<hi>'s Reaſon for it</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Their uncharitable Raſhneſs condemn'd, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to the Biſhop's Pride</hi> 44.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:48306:64"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>What Supplemental Proviſion ſeemeth deſirable upon ſome Neceſſities</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the Qualification of Perſons to be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,</hi> viz. <hi>Baptiſm and Prae-inſtruction in the Church-Catechiſm at Years of Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 45.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Preface read to that purpoſe at</hi> Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation 46.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Queſtion then alſo put by the Biſhop, and anſwered by all the Candidates</hi> 47.</item>
                     <item>Aquinas <hi>and</hi> Contarenus <hi>of another mind; but diſlik'd by the later</hi> Romaniſts <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> 48.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Benefit of this Sacred Right depends much upon a competent Growth of Age and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>No prejudice by deferring it till then, by our Churches Declaration.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A ſerious Exhortation to all that come on this Errand</hi> 49.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the great Importance and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs of this whole Tranſaction, in five particulars</hi> 50.</item>
                     <item>Melchiades <hi>his Epiſtle to the Biſhops of</hi> Spain <hi>in Vindication of it</hi> 54.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſame more largely from</hi> Euſebius Emiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, <hi>or</hi> Eucherius Lugdun. <hi>Homilie on</hi> Pentecoſt 55.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Summary of the Graces and Bleſſings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent out of</hi> Biſhop Taylor 56.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:48306:64"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Concluding Admonition to all perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, not to diſgrace ſo well grounded Principles, by an unſuitable Practice, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced from Mr.</hi> Hooker 58.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Jackſon, <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond, <hi>and Dr. Hench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> 59.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Contents of the</hi> Appendix.</head>
                     <item>T <hi>C's Objections againſt</hi> Confirmation 61.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Hooker's <hi>Anſwer to the ſame</hi> 62.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A Tranſlation of ſome admirable Paſſages out of Dr.</hi> Hammond, De Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione 65.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>An uſeful Deſcription of Confirmation from all the Premiſſes</hi> 68.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>Contents of the Sermon Annexed.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of the Firſt Plantation of the Church of</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch 72.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>St.</hi> Barnabas <hi>ſent thither from</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to Confirm.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>How he was affected with Joy at the ſight of their hopeful Beginnings</hi> 73.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>How he endeavor'd to encourage and hearten them to an anſwerable Perſeverance</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:48306:65"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of coming and cleaving unto Chriſt in the Scripture Sence</hi> 76.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Of that purpoſe of Heart wherewith it is to be done</hi> 82.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Including a</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Perſonal Reſolution of Soul. ibid.</item>
                           <item>Sincere Reſolution of Soul. 87.</item>
                           <item>Deliberate Reſolution of Soul. 90.</item>
                           <item>Free Reſolution of Soul. 95.</item>
                           <item>Firm Reſolution of Soul. 98.</item>
                           <item>Zealo us Reſolution of soul. 100.</item>
                           <item>Humble Reſolution of Soul. 101.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>General Motive and Exhortations to inforce this Exhortation.</hi> 103.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48306:65"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
